<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Kalōz telōnēsantai or, The excise-man Shewing the excellency of his profession, how and in what it precedes all others; the felicity he enjoys, the pleasures as well as qualifications that inevitably attend him, notwithstanding the opprobrious calunmies of the most inveterate detractor. Discovering his knowledge in the arts, men and laws in an essay. By Ezekiel Polsted, A.B.</title>
            <author>Polsted, Ezekiel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2780B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218302</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829910</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829910</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34357</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55329)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34357)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2012:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Kalōz telōnēsantai or, The excise-man Shewing the excellency of his profession, how and in what it precedes all others; the felicity he enjoys, the pleasures as well as qualifications that inevitably attend him, notwithstanding the opprobrious calunmies of the most inveterate detractor. Discovering his knowledge in the arts, men and laws in an essay. By Ezekiel Polsted, A.B.</title>
                  <author>Polsted, Ezekiel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by John Mayos, at the Colden Cross in Thames-street near Queenhithe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First 2 words of title in Greek.</note>
                  <note>Title page is A2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Professions --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34357:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR, THE <hi>Exciſe-Man.</hi> Shewing The <hi>Excellency</hi> of his <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> how and in what it precedes all others; the <hi>Felicity</hi> he enjoys, the <hi>Pleaſures</hi> as well as <hi>Qualifications</hi> that inevitably attend him, notwithſtanding the opprobrious <hi>Calumnies</hi> of the moſt inveterate <hi>Detractor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcovering his Knowledge in the ARTS, MEN and LAWS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In an Eſſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>EZEKIEL POLSTED,</hi> A.B.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Nor ſhall my <hi>Muſe</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcend</l>
               <l>To Clap with ſuch who <hi>Knaves</hi> and <hi>Fools</hi> commend,</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Smiles</hi> and <hi>Cenſures</hi> are to me the ſame,</l>
               <l>I care not what they <hi>praiſe,</hi> or what they <hi>blame.</hi>
               </l>
               <bibl>Dryden in Juvenal.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>John Mayos,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Croſs</hi> in <hi>Thames-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Queenhithe.</hi> 1697.
<pb facs="tcp:34357:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:34357:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34357:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34357:3"/>
            <head>To the Honoured
<list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Stephen Evans,</hi> Kts.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Foche,</hi> Kts.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Francis Parry,</hi> Eſqs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Strong,</hi> Eſqs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Clark,</hi> Eſqs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Foot Onſlow,</hi> Eſqs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Danvers,</hi> Eſqs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philip Medows,</hi> Eſqs</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Everard,</hi> Eſqs</item>
               </list>
Chief Commiſſioners and Governors for the Management and Receipt of His Majeſties Revenue of <hi>Exciſe</hi> within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere not your <hi>Candor</hi> and <hi>Clemency</hi> as eminently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to every <hi>Criminal,</hi> as are
<pb facs="tcp:34357:4"/>Your <hi>piercing Judgments</hi> to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, he muſt be poſſeſs'd with a more than <hi>ſhivering Extaſy,</hi> that ſhould preſume to accoſt You with the preſent <hi>Dedication:</hi> For though the following <hi>Paper</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in great <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of ſuch <hi>Patrons,</hi> yet that it ſhould be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition'd by ſo perfect a <hi>Stranger,</hi> and that without a <hi>Licence,</hi> might create a Wonder beyond the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the moſt Credulous. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, <hi>Ingratitude</hi> having been ever eſteem'd the <hi>Epitome</hi> of <hi>all Vices,</hi> and, conſequently, the Guilt of the <hi>former,</hi> being much more eligible, with all imaginable <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> I crave Leave to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent You with the grateful Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Kingdom for Your <hi>Impartial Adminiſtration,</hi> whereby You have taken a <hi>Charter of the
<pb facs="tcp:34357:4"/>Peoples Hearts, never to be can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not be guilty of an <hi>Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Preſumption,</hi> by deſcending to <hi>Particulars,</hi> but moſt humbly <hi>implore a Pardon</hi> for ſubjoining, that Your <hi>Endeavours</hi> have been <hi>vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> beyond a <hi>Preſident,</hi> in Your <hi>equally</hi> aſſerting <hi>His Majeſty's</hi> and the <hi>Countries Rights,</hi> by encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging any thing that has but the <hi>Tincture</hi> of <hi>Probity</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> and wholly <hi>exploding</hi> and <hi>diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing</hi> that <hi>Rigor,</hi> which has been uſually perpetrated under the ſpecious Pretext of <hi>Law:</hi> Theſe are ſo publickly known, and ſuch uncommon Actions, as will be Regiſter'd in every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudic'd Breaſt, till Time it ſelf ſhall have an End; by which we
<pb facs="tcp:34357:5"/>find You acquieſce in the Opinion of the <hi>Great Ageſilaus,</hi> who dying in his Voyage from <hi>Egypt,</hi> forbad any <hi>Statue</hi> in memorial of <hi>Him,</hi> ſaying, <hi>He had left thoſe Actions behind him, as would render it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſignificant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe being ſuch great <hi>Verities</hi> as admit not of a <hi>Contradiction,</hi> we have Reaſon to be aſſur'd, That by Your extraordinary Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, the <hi>Exciſe,</hi> like the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian Ship,</hi> by being ſo often mended, will in a ſhort time ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to that perfection, that there never will be found a <hi>rotten</hi> or <hi>imperfect Stick:</hi> And therefore pray, That <hi>Health</hi> (which gives the only <hi>Reliſh</hi> to all Your out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Enjoyments) and <hi>Proſperity,</hi> may be Your conſtant <hi>Slaves</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:34357:5"/>
               <hi>Lacquies;</hi> That a continu'd Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of all <hi>Terreſtrial Felicities</hi> may ever court You; And that You may ever move as <hi>Refulgent Stars</hi> in the <hi>Orb</hi> You are plac'd, for the encouragement of <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> and deſtruction of every Action that might carry the <hi>Epithet</hi> of <hi>Ill:</hi> And althô 'tis uſual to wiſh You <hi>many Years,</hi> yet I ſhall wiſh You but <hi>ONE:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—<hi>Sed Annus</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hic, mea ſi valeant Vota,</hi> Platonis <hi>erit.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am <hi>(Honoured Sirs) Your moſt humble and Obedient Servant,</hi> Ezekiel Polſted.</signed>
               <dateline>Lond. Calend. <date>Januar. An. 1697.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:34357:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34357:6"/>
            <head>TO THE Gentlemen Employ'd in the REVENUE OF EXCISE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE many <hi>Reflections</hi> which have been caſt on your <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> induc'd me to an exact <hi>Examination</hi> of their <hi>Merit,</hi> and finding them to be wholly the <hi>Reſult of Malice and
<pb facs="tcp:34357:7"/>Ignorance,</hi> I could not avoid this <hi>Publick Confeſſion</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, Your <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Favours to me,</hi> command a much greater Acknowledgment than Expreſſion is capable of giving, yet I think, my ſelf ſufficiently happy, that I have an opportunity of telling the World ſo, and conſequently, that your <hi>Favours</hi> and my <hi>Gratitude</hi> are equally illimitable; which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration has wholly occaſion'd this Trouble, and therefore the <hi>innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Cenſures</hi> that muſt inevitably attend it, are extremely below my Concern; for I muſt own, that I ſhall receive them with an extraordinary <hi>Pride,</hi> ſince it muſt be thought too, it was <hi>wholly for your ſakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The following Vindication then,
<pb facs="tcp:34357:7"/>ſuch as it is, I preſent you with, and thô it might poſſibly be thought to <hi>want one it ſelf,</hi> or that your <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency</hi> is ſuch, as to render it <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together inſignificant,</hi> yet I muſt aver, that I can very <hi>calmly</hi> receive the <hi>former,</hi> provided the <hi>latter</hi> does not as <hi>unanſwerably intervene:</hi> Thô conſidering that the <hi>Illiterate</hi> make up the <hi>greateſt part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> I preſume it not <hi>impertinent</hi> ſometimes to anſwer them in their <hi>own Terms;</hi> for all the <hi>Reflections</hi> in the following Paper, are only beſtow'd on <hi>ſuch,</hi> who are ſo maliciouſly extravagant in giving them.</p>
            <p>I am extreamly ſenſible of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining you too long from your <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing Felcities,</hi> and therefore ſhall ſay nothing to the <hi>Gentle Reader,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:34357:8"/>but only acquaint <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>all the World,</hi> that your innumerable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations have created ſuch grateful Sentiments, as ſhall meet with a Duration that can never terminate, as being</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your humble Servant, <hi>Ezekiel Polſted.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lond. Calend.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Januar. 1697.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:34357:8"/>
            <head>ON THE Author <hi>and</hi> Subject.</head>
            <l>Bravely <hi>begun,</hi> and bravely <hi>ended</hi> too,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Arts</hi> receive their <hi>Character</hi> from you;</l>
            <l>They gratefully attend you, ſince th' <hi>EXCISE,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Exact Perfection in it ſelf implies:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Arithmetick</hi> is ſhort, in vain we ſtrive</l>
            <l>To find, that which no Rule could ever give;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Addition</hi> here a quick <hi>Subſtraction</hi> meets</l>
            <l>As to the <hi>happy Perſons,</hi> as the <hi>Sheets;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For by the <hi>bold Attempt</hi> we must ſubmit,</l>
            <l>That to your <hi>Fame</hi> whatever can be writ,</l>
            <l>Like<note n="*" place="bottom">Decimal Arithmetick.</note> 
               <hi>Right-Hand Cyphers</hi> only leſſens it.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>John Morgan—Junior de Wenalt in Com' Brecon.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:34357:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ALI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>D,</hi> TO THE Officers <hi>of the</hi> Exciſe.</head>
            <l>WE own'd your <hi>Power,</hi> and the <hi>Pleaſures</hi> too</l>
            <l>That, as their <hi>Center,</hi> ever meet in you;</l>
            <l>But your <hi>monopolizing Senſe</hi> affords</l>
            <l>A Raviſhment, beyond the <hi>Pow'r</hi> of Words:</l>
            <l>To <hi>Silence</hi> thus <hi>Conſin'd,</hi> I must obey,</l>
            <l>And only <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſay,</hi> that I can <hi>nothing ſay.</hi>
            </l>
            <bibl>Henry Vaughan <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iluriſt.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34357:9"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR, THE Exciſe-Man.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing that is a greater Subject of <hi>Admiration,</hi> or has crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more <hi>Wonder</hi> in me, than the great <hi>Difference</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of ſome perſons <hi>attaining,</hi> and others again <hi>miſſing, Preferment;</hi> and the <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Methods</hi> conducing thereunto: it often <hi>wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon <hi>ſome</hi> without either <hi>Endeavour</hi> or <hi>Merit,</hi> and as often flies <hi>thoſe</hi> who are moſt excellently qualified in <hi>Both.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I confeſs I could never gueſs at the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of this ſo ſeemingly great a piece of <hi>Injuſtice,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:34357:10"/>unleſs they may be applicable to one of the two ſubſequent (I beg pardon for calling them) <hi>Reaſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then, If you'll believe the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> there are <hi>ſome</hi> that are <hi>unfortunate</hi> even in their <hi>Nativity,</hi> or (as they call it) <hi>Diis ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micis atque iratis, vel malo aſtro natus,</hi> born under an unlucky <hi>Planet;</hi> ſo that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Induſtry, Misfortunes</hi> and they are <hi>yok'd,</hi> and under a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made inſeparable Companions. This ſeems to be an unreaſonable <hi>Impoſition,</hi> and the <hi>Perſons</hi> that ſo unfortunately <hi>groan</hi> under it, are not to be accounted <hi>culpable,</hi> ſince the rigour of their <hi>Fate</hi> has made it <hi>indiſpenſible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, If the <hi>Cauſe</hi> is not thus infallib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>obligatory,</hi> another may be the reſult of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertency</hi> or <hi>Fear,</hi> (either of which may be reckon'd our own Crime) which may occaſion us the miſſing that <hi>Critical Minute,</hi> which the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſay if it be not embrac'd, never preſents it ſelf more—<hi>Stat ſua cuique dies.</hi> Every one has his time.</p>
               <q>Aeſt as non ſemper fuerit componite nidos—</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Strike</hi> while the <hi>Iron</hi> is <hi>hot,</hi> and you <hi>anvil</hi> our what you <hi>pleaeſe;</hi> whereas once <hi>cold,</hi> you meet with an <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> to <hi>effect</hi> that, which before you might have <hi>perfected</hi> with the greateſt <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34357:10"/>
               <p>Well then! our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> being thus much reſin'd from <hi>common Earth,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently having been ſo fortunate as to eſcape the <hi>firſt,</hi> and ſo prudent as to <hi>ſeize</hi> the laſt, he is liſted in the large (excuſe me for the preſumption of <hi>Senſible</hi>) <hi>Roll</hi> of His Majeſties <hi>Officers:</hi> when he is no ſooner accoſted with Expreſſions ſuitable to their <hi>Authors;</hi> That he <hi>is the perfection of Scandal and Infamy,</hi> the <hi>general</hi> reſult <hi>of a Broken Shop,</hi> and <hi>Intellerable Burthens, which the world has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready too much troubled with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſatisfie the Rational part then, were the following lines thought of, that they may be aſſur'd, that that <hi>Employment</hi> is not manag'd by <hi>thoſe,</hi> who are beyond exception contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to (at leaſt) <hi>common ſence;</hi> Or are ſuch perfect <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to any <hi>pleaſure</hi> the World is Capable of giving, but <hi>far Exceed</hi> any <hi>particular ſort</hi> (if not all) <hi>Mankind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this will inſtantly convince them, ſince it's never oppos'd but by the <hi>Ignorant (Ars non habet inimicum praeter Ignorantem)</hi> who not only <hi>know them not,</hi> but are not <hi>capable of doing it;</hi> and inded nothing leſs can be Expected from thoſe who are not unfitly compar'd to one of their <hi>Barrels,</hi> that is wholy <hi>Empty,</hi> for they cannot come into Competition with an <hi>Eighth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:34357:11"/>
               <p>In ſhort, theſe are the moſt capable of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy in the <hi>Famous</hi> and <hi>Learned Norcia</hi> (a Town in the <hi>Apennines</hi> 25 miles from <hi>Rome</hi> and belongs to a <hi>Cardinal</hi>) of which<note n="*" place="margin">Sup. to Dr. <hi>Burnets</hi> Let. <hi>p. 79.</hi>
                  </note> a late <hi>Author</hi> gives this incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Character, That though it lyes within the <hi>Popes</hi> Territories, yet no Man can have a ſhare in their <hi>Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that can <hi>Write</hi> or <hi>Read:</hi> So that their <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> which conſiſts of four Perſons, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in the hands of <hi>(Li quatri illuerati)</hi> the four Illiterate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh! Jam ſatis eſt o he!</hi> 'Tis certainly high time to conclude, and, were I capable, ought to <hi>Apologize</hi> for pretending to characterize him, who cannot without regret view any Man whom Fortune ſeems to favour; who cannot with any Satisfaction endure the praiſing any but himſelf, whoſe torments are <hi>antarctiek</hi> to all other <hi>Diſturbances,</hi> ſince he makes felicity the cauſe of his Infelicity, and any Mans wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, the Occaſion of his Sickneſs; whoſe good Opinion none can purchaſe, but at the Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Rate of being eternally undone; and ſhall therefore conclude with the <hi>Epigrammatift</hi>—</p>
               <q>Captivum Line te, tenet Ignorantia duplex, Scis nihil, &amp; neſcis te quoque Scire nihil.</q>
               <p>Twice ignorant you are, 'tis Strange yet true, Nothing you know, and yet moſt wretched you Know not, that ever yet you nothing knew.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:34357:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>AS it's very obſervable, there was never any <hi>Emhuſiaſt</hi> that ſet up for immediate Revelations, deriving thereby a pretended Authority to utter his Nonſenſical and <hi>Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> Notions, but has acquir'd <hi>ſome Proſelues</hi> (either <hi>weak Women</hi> or <hi>weaher Men</hi>) let them he ever ſo Abſurd and Ridiculous; And as there was never any <hi>Mountebank</hi> or <hi>Empyrick in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,</hi> let him be as <hi>Empty</hi> as his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinal,</hi> and as void of Learning, as a <hi>Jockey of Honeſty,</hi> yet this <hi>Catholick Block-head,</hi> what by his <hi>French Muſtacho's</hi> and broken <hi>Engliſh,</hi> has gain'd ſome <hi>Patients<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to maintain the <hi>Pluſh-jacquet</hi> of the <hi>Cobling</hi> Doctor, ſo its indubitable, that let an Aſperſion be caſt on any Officer, by the moſt <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitid Brute</hi> of the Creation, he ſhall not only meet with almoſt innumerable Abettors, but be held in eternal Admiration for his <hi>ingeaious Pnn,</hi> whereas its connection is the ſame our <hi>Poet</hi> ſpeaks of.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So have I ſeen the Pride of Nature's Store,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The</hi> Orient Pearl <hi>chain'd to the</hi> Sooty Morr;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So hath the Diamonds</hi> Bright Ray <hi>been ſet</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In</hi> night, <hi>and</hi> wedded <hi>to the</hi> Nigro jett,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Like</hi> Dolphins <hi>ranging in the ſhady</hi> Wood,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And</hi> Savage Boars <hi>are</hi> Swiming on the Flood.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:34357:12"/>
               <p>So that, although it meets with as great a Contrariety as the expectation of the <hi>Smokes deſcending</hi> (it being a perfect contradiction, and <hi>Heterogeneous</hi> in nature) yet it would make one ſtagger, to ſee how he values himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his luckie thought, and happy reflection, whereas there was nothing a fitter Subject for laughter and deteſtation.</p>
               <p>I remember a Story of an Ingenious Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whoſe <hi>Coat</hi> happening to be made ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too <hi>ſhort,</hi> our <hi>Wit</hi> immediately cenſur'd it, the <hi>Gentleman</hi> told him it would be <hi>long enough</hi> before he ſhould have <hi>another,</hi> which he admir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note n="*" place="margin">Nihil eſt quin male nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando poſſit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravarier.</note> reſolv'd to make it his own by a repetition in another Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; and told them, <hi>it</hi> would be a <hi>great while</hi> before he ſhould have another, leaving out the word <hi>long,</hi> wherein the whole (if there was any) Wit lay; yet, I ſay, meets with no ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, becauſe it flows from ſuch inſpir'd Lips, whereas he conſiders not the <hi>Rationale,</hi> which is <hi>indigna digna habenda ſunt quae Herus facit:</hi> So that it being generally the reſult of the flattery of an <hi>inferior</hi> (to gratifie a more <hi>ignorant Superior</hi>) we ſhall look upon it as ſuch, and equally value it as that <hi>King</hi> did his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor,</hi> who to humour his <hi>Soveraign, ſaw</hi> that <hi>inviſible Star.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34357:12"/>
               <p>Whether theſe merit the name of <hi>Men of Parts,</hi> that ſhall thus admit of ſuch an <hi>Impoſition,</hi> we ſhall not here diſpute; but that it generally prevails, may not only be prov'd by what has been ſaid, but even out of the <hi>Ancients</hi> themſelves: <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Qualification in that <hi>Art,</hi> gain'd the good Opinion of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> far more than <hi>Dyon</hi> the <hi>Syracuſan</hi> could by his <hi>Plain dealing;</hi> as did alſo <hi>Cleo</hi> beyond <hi>Caliſthenes</hi> with <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That theſe with the <hi>Androgeni</hi> in <hi>Pliny</hi> are as variable as Thought, or with Wax receive any Impreſſion, may be allow'd of, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that they take even a ſuggeſtion for granted thô it be Malice in the <hi>Abſtract;</hi> and are ſo prodigiouſly Weak, as not to know, that it is only pretended to by thoſe, who have an <hi>Eternal Dependance;</hi> nay, this often arrives to that exceſs, that it frequently expoſes them to the <hi>Epithet of Ridiculous:</hi> Thus <hi>Caryſophus</hi> laugh'd becauſe his Maſter <hi>Dionyſius</hi> did, though he knew not for what; which he ſeeing, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Cauſe: <hi>Caryſophus</hi> reply'd, <hi>I think that which creates Laughter in you, is worth Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at.</hi> Thus <hi>Clyſophus</hi> when <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> halted becauſe of the <hi>Gout,</hi> he diſſembled the ſame Imperfection. Accordingly, what you deny he forſwears; what you affirm, he juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies; if you weep he is ſad; if you laugh he is merry; and all this while in reality neither,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34357:13"/>but in obliging thoſe on which <hi>inſinuating obſervance</hi> their <hi>ſubſiſtance</hi> does depend.</p>
               <p>It cannot but be acknowledg'd, that I have dwelt much too long on this ſubject, but it ſo often and immediately concerning the <hi>Perſons</hi> I am pretending to vindicate, I hope an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe will be eaſily admitted of, and ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Conclude with his Character in Brief: <hi>He is before hand with your thoughts, and able to ſuggeſt them unto you. He will commend to you firſt what he knows you like; and hath always ſome abſurd. Story or other of your Enemy, and then wonders how your two opinious ſhould ſo jump to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Theſe look upon their <hi>Betters</hi> with a <hi>Scorn,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thus their <hi>Cloudy-heads</hi> are highly <hi>born,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſo by <hi>Straws</hi> are empty'd heads of <hi>Corn.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:34357:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THat there can be any thing more intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable than <hi>unmerited Reflections</hi> is ſo palpably True, that it would be altogether impertinent to enforce its <hi>Demonſtration:</hi> And although in ſuch a <hi>large Community,</hi> it would be almoſt next to an Impoſſibility to expect, that every one ſhould be exempted from them; yet ſince the <hi>Majority at leaſt</hi> muſt be allow'd to be ſo, he muſt arrive to a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Degree of Aſſurance,</hi> that ſhould therefore <hi>conclude</hi> the <hi>ſame</hi> of the <hi>Whole.</hi> So that a <hi>ſingle</hi> (ſuppoſe a bad) Action perpetrated by a <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Member,</hi> is no more to be attributed to the <hi>Society,</hi> than that the <hi>profligate Life</hi> of one <hi>Perſon</hi> ſhould be ſuppoſed to be allow'd of, and tollerated by the <hi>Religion</hi> he outwardly makes a Profeſſion of; which continually explodes and deteſts it, ſince he is hourly endeavour'd to be unmasked and detected, by all the Care and Inſpection Imaginable.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore acquieſce, as ſuppoſe it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd of, by the Unprejudiced, that <hi>each one</hi> bears the <hi>Scandal</hi> that is the infallible Reſult of his own <hi>particular Crimes.</hi> And here only obſerve, That the general Objection to their Happineſs is, that they are Vagabonds, Out-Comers,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34357:14"/>Ubiquitarians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and conſequently think it not improper to affirm, that abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the <hi>Pleaſures, Profits</hi> and <hi>Qualifications</hi> hereafter ſpecified, that inevitably attend our Exciſe-Man; yet there is ſomewhat more to be ſaid in his <hi>Vindication,</hi> and that therefore the Objection is naturally Frivolous, Falſe and Erronious.</p>
               <p>We all know that <hi>ſtanding Lakes</hi> and <hi>Pools</hi> are never <hi>clear or wholeſome,</hi> and thoſe deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <hi>Fogs</hi> and <hi>Miſts,</hi> which ever proceed from them, have always no ſmall <hi>influence upon the adjacent Inhabitants,</hi> whereas thoſe pleaſing (becauſe rapid) Streams, being in perpetual Motion, wholly remove the Cauſe which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly ingenders their Contagion.</p>
               <p>Again, we are poſitive, by ocular Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, that <hi>Trees themſelves</hi> cannot poſſibly bear ſuch delicious Fruit where they were <hi>Originally fixed,</hi> as when they are <hi>tranſplanted;</hi> and the moſt <hi>bewitching Perfumes</hi> are wholly <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant,</hi> and render not their Odeurs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the motion of being <hi>rubbed</hi> and <hi>chafed.</hi> And we alſo all know that the fixed Stars are not of that account or eſteem, as thoſe that have continual Motion.</p>
               <p>But our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> knows an additional <hi>Rejoynder</hi> in his own <hi>Vindication,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very pertinently expreſſed by the <hi>Epigrammatiſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Owen <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 100.</note> I preſume there is no neceſſity of <hi>Apologizing</hi> for its <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:34357:14"/>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Illa mihi</hi> Patria <hi>eſt, ubi</hi> paſcor, <hi>non ubi</hi> naſcor:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Illa ubi ſum</hi> Notus, <hi>non ubi</hi> Natus <hi>eram.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Illa mihi</hi> Patria <hi>eſt, mihi quae</hi> Patrimonia <hi>praebet;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hic, ubicunque habeo quod ſatis eſt, habito.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My Country is where're my <hi>Bread</hi> I get,</l>
                     <l>Not where I was <hi>Bred,</hi> but where I have <hi>Meat:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where I am <hi>known</hi> not <hi>Chriſten'd;</hi> there I dwell</l>
                     <l>(And no where elſe) wherever I do well.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34357:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>BEfore we come to demonſtrate the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Excellencies</hi> that inevitably attend the <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Employment</hi> of our <hi>Exciſe-Man,</hi> above the loweſt dregs of Men, the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and the Felicity he enjoys, notwithſtanding the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Cenſures of the moſt Critically Cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; it may not be amiſs to obſerve, that there might be ſomething <hi>ab initio</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly reſpecting him;<note place="margin">Haec Homo.</note> For as ſome compare his Head to the Round Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, his Eyes to the Sun and Moon, his Hairs to the Trees and Graſs; his Fleſh to the Earth; his Veins to the Rivers, and his Bones to the precious Gems, Metals and Minerals, which are the Riches of the Earth; ſo ſome have been led to imagine, that his Body was not made in all the <hi>Geometrical Proportions</hi> that are or can be thought of, but as a <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of the <hi>Excellency</hi> of our <hi>Exciſe-Man,</hi> who ſhould make the greateſt uſe of them.</p>
               <p>For all Numbers and Proportions of Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whether Inches, Cubits, Feet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are deriv'd from the Members and Dimenſions of Him, ſome few of which may not be imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſubjoin'd.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:34357:15"/>
               <p>Firſt then, Let us ſee how a <hi>Circle</hi> was thought of; for let but the Hands fall ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtradling a little with the Legs, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes of the Fingers, Head and Toes, make as exact a Circle as you are capable of making with your Unerring Compaſſes, where you may, if you pleaſe, make the <hi>Navel</hi> the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, A <hi>Geometrical Square is a Superficial Figure made up of four equal Sides or Angles:</hi> Now for a Demonſtration of this Figure from Man's Body, it is but ſtretching out your Hands as far and directly upon a Plane as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible from each ſide, the Body being exactly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and the Feet clos'd together.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, A <hi>Triangle is a Figure containing three Sides:</hi> Now if the Body be plac'd directly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and a Line drawn from each extended Hand, to the Feet enclos'd, it makes an exact <hi>Triangle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Several other <hi>Geometrical Figures</hi> might be deduc'd from Humane Bodies, but ſince Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixity is never obliging, and not at all correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondent to my preſent Deſign, (which wholly aims at Brevity) I ſhall now wave it, and leave the curious Enquirer to his further Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the reſt.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:34357:16"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Thus <hi>ab Origine,</hi> we find</l>
                  <l>His Excellencies were deſign'd:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Geometry</hi> muſt Him confeſs</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Center</hi> of each Happineſs;</l>
                  <l>For as their <hi>Patron, Him</hi> alone</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Mathematicks</hi> wait upon.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:34357:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing of <hi>Excellency</hi> but is atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with <hi>difficulty,</hi> for where any thing is obtain'd without it, it forthwith ceaſes to be <hi>excellent;</hi> Could every <hi>Mechanick</hi> be a Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in the ſucceeding <hi>Arts,</hi> who would eſteem them Excellent? And could every <hi>Illiterate</hi> be a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> its excellency would quickly ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in a mean Opinion: Could every <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Ruſtick</hi> attain to a perfect knowledge in the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> its Excellency would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into Contempt; So that <hi>difficulty</hi> being an inſeparable <hi>Attendant</hi> on every Art that can properly aſſume the Epithet of <hi>Excellent,</hi> it is the chiefeſt cauſe of its <hi>Eſtimation;</hi> whereas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, the Excellency that now deſervedly waits upon them, would quickly dwindle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and they be render'd wholly deſpicable, if not Scandalous, and altogether unworthy to be attain'd, much leſs to be had in the leaſt Eſteem or Veneration.</p>
               <p>For Demonſtration then, that they have climb'd over the chiefeſt Excellencies that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly attend the following Arts, we do poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirm, <hi>That if an Excellent inſpection in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the general parts of the Mathematicks will create eſtimation,</hi> if <hi>an abſolute knowledge</hi> of <hi>Vulgar</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34357:17"/>
                  <hi>Decimal Arithmetick will produce Commendation:</hi> Or, if a great proficiency in <hi>Geometry</hi> will me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>Admiration,</hi> our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> claims them all by Undeniable <hi>Preſcription.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He can tell you that the <hi>Mathematicks</hi> in General, <hi>Are thoſe Arts and Sciences which carry along with them the irreſiſtible force of Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tien;</hi> which are inſtanc'd in the following Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, <hi>viz. Arithmetick, Geometry, Muſick, and Aſtronomy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We cannot exclude him from a Competent knowledge in them all, but muſt aver an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in the <hi>two firſt:</hi> And ſhall therefore only tell you here, that he knows <hi>Arithmetick</hi> to be an Art of <hi>Numbering</hi> well; and if you would be fully ſatisfied herein, Conſult the Books already expo'sd by many Eminent <hi>Gaugers</hi> on it.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Geometry,</hi> he can tell you that it is an <hi>Art of due proportion</hi> or Meaſuring (the Earth) and that it contains three kinds of Magnitude (according to that Exquiſite Artiſt Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> in his <hi>Gauger's Magazin</hi>) <hi>viz. Lines, Surfaces,</hi> and <hi>Solids,</hi> Nature not admitting of any more; <hi>Length, Breadth,</hi> and <hi>Depth,</hi> taking up the whole of Space.</p>
               <p>He tells you a Line hath only <hi>Length</hi> whoſe <hi>Boundaries</hi> are <hi>points;</hi> a <hi>Surface</hi> hath <hi>Length</hi> and <hi>Breadth,</hi> whoſe <hi>Boundaries</hi> are <hi>Lines;</hi> and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34357:17"/>that a ſolid hath <hi>length, breadth,</hi> and <hi>depth,</hi> or <hi>thickneſs,</hi> whoſe Boundaries are <hi>Surfaces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He further informs you, that every of theſe three kinds of <hi>Magnitude</hi> is Meaſur'd by ſome known kind of <hi>Magnitude,</hi> that is <hi>Homogenial,</hi> or like to it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> A line is Meaſur'd by a line, as one lineal Inch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a Surface by a Surface, as one Square, Inch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and a Solid by a Solid, as one Solid Inch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when it is known how many Lineal Inches are contain'd in a Line, Square in a Surface, or Solid in a Solid, then is the Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity or Content of either of theſe Magnitudes ſaid to be known.</p>
               <p>Thus far in General, and I muſt beg the Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending of your Expectations of Particulars, until I acquaint you, that notwithſtanding our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi>'s prudence, oblig'd him not to omit the graſping this <hi>critical opportunity,</hi> yet he was not Ignorant of the impoſſibility of arriving to any allowable proficiency in theſe incomparable Speculations, without a <hi>corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent Genius,</hi> and <hi>natural Inclination;</hi> for he knows very well, that what <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid of <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> (and which himſelf found too true in his Intolerable <hi>O Fortunatam natam me Conſule Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam</hi>) that it was not poſſible to be a <hi>Poet</hi> by Rule or Precept; ſo is it here, for without an <hi>agreeable Inſtinct,</hi> he can never advance to any perfection in them, in regard they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34357:18"/>Demonſtration along with them; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the Hiſtories the world has ever produced, we can find very few (if any) that have prov'd themſelves any way eminent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; for as they inform us, that as <hi>Socrates</hi> after he had learn'd the Art of <hi>Poeſie</hi> by <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rems,</hi> yet was he not ever capable of making one verſe: So cannot we find the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Euclid</hi> any way famous, take him out of his own <hi>Element.</hi> This we ſee alſo ſufficiently demonſtrated in <hi>Mark</hi> the Son of the unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd <hi>Cicero,</hi> who notwithſtanding his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's ſevere Injunctions, admirable Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, together with the aſſiſtance of <hi>Athens</hi> the then moſt Celebrated <hi>Academy</hi> of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; yet I ſay, not being poſſeſs'd with this <hi>innate tendency,</hi> he prov'd in the end but a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Contempt and Scorn.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> then finding this Sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grafted in him, he Cheerfully proceeds.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Tho <hi>Criticks,</hi> like the <hi>Dog Snarl</hi> at the Stone,</l>
                  <l>Condemning that which is too hard a Bone</l>
                  <l>For their thin Chaps to deal with—all withſtand</l>
                  <l>Abuſing <hi>moſt,</hi> what they <hi>leaſt</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I had here (according to promiſe) intended a particular Extract of his <hi>Excellencies</hi> in the preceding <hi>Arts,</hi> Demonſtrating his Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Common-Brewer, Diſtiller,</hi> and <hi>Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aller,</hi> out of the Incomparable <hi>Stentography</hi> of the Honour'd Mr. <hi>Everard,</hi> the Exquiſite
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34357:18"/>
                  <hi>Magazin</hi> of Mr. <hi>Hunt,</hi> the Ingenious <hi>Gauger's Practice</hi> of Mr. <hi>Ward,</hi> and all others who have arriv'd to any Eminency in thoſe Inimitable Qualifications: But ſhall at preſent ſuſpend my intentions herein, in regard I find this part increaſing too conſiderably on my Hands, and only here obſerve, that were the knowledge of moſt of his Cenſuring <hi>Criticks</hi> herein queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, their anſwers would be wholly as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent as the Queſtion of the following <hi>Norcian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A young Gentleman in the time of <hi>Popery,</hi> coming from the Univerſity, his Father had an extraordinary deſire to know what Proficiency he had made, and in order thereunto deſires an Eminent <hi>Monk</hi> to ſatisfie his Curioſity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by a Particular Examination, who being (no doubt) very ſenſible of his own parts, boldly accoſts with,</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What was Latin for a <hi>Prieſt?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sacerdos,</hi> which was deny'd, and affirm'd to be <hi>Sapientia,</hi> becauſe of his great <hi>Wiſdom.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is Latin for a <hi>Cat?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Felis,</hi> which was contradicted, and told <hi>Aſper,</hi> becauſe of her Sharp Nails.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is for <hi>Fire?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ignis,</hi> but he was aſſur'd it was <hi>Letitia,</hi> for what can produce more Gladneſs in cold Weather?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>What is for <hi>Water?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:34357:19"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aqua,</hi> no ſays the <hi>Monk,</hi> it is <hi>Abundantia,</hi> becauſe of the abundance of it in <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>Laſtly, he ask'd him what was Latin for a <hi>Barn?</hi> the <hi>Scholar</hi> replying <hi>Horreun,</hi> was confronted and told <hi>Gaudium,</hi> for what great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Joy then a <hi>Barn</hi> full of Corn: Well! this heat being over, the <hi>former</hi> was <hi>applauded</hi> for his <hi>profound</hi> parts, and the <hi>latter diſcarded</hi> for his <hi>Ignorance;</hi> who thereupon took a <hi>Cat,</hi> and tying a <hi>Fire-Brand</hi> to her tayl, threw her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Monk's</hi> Barn, and cry'd out, <hi>O Sapientia, Sapientia, Aſper currit cum Letitia, &amp; ſi non veneris cum abundantia, munquam intrabis in gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium tuum;</hi> who for getting his Elaborate La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, was immediately ruin'd.</p>
               <p>But not to be Impertinently prolix, I ſhall conclude, that ſince <hi>there is nothing of Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy but is attended with Difficulty,</hi> as has been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, and that ſince he has wholly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome the difficulties that wait on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Arts, I muſt not ſay he is therefore <hi>Excellent,</hi> but I muſt aver <hi>(fiat Juſtitia &amp; ruat coelum)</hi> he merits a far greater Character than he or they deſire, but
<q>
                     <hi>Marmoreo Licinus tumulo jacet, at Cato parvo, Pompeius nullo, quis putet eſſe Deos?</hi>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Licinus</hi> doth in Marble Sleep,</l>
                        <l>A Common Urn doth <hi>Cato</hi> keep,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Aſhes may catch cold,</l>
                        <l>That there are <hi>Gods,</hi> let <hi>Dotards</hi> hold.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:34357:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>HAving thus, with all the Brevity imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, run over ſome of thoſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Qualifications</hi> that attend our <hi>Exciſe-Man,</hi> and his <hi>Excellency in the preceding Arts,</hi> I ſhall ſubjoin ſome few Lines in relation to his knowledge of <hi>Men;</hi> for he knows very well, that though the reading of <hi>Books</hi> cannot but be own'd to be extremely advantageous, if rightly underſtood, yet he alſo knows it to be wholly uſeleſs, without putting the Notions it inſinuates into practice; which <hi>reading of Men</hi> conſiſts chiefly (at lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in my Opinion) in a regular Behaviour on all Emergencies, that he does not <hi>ignorantly impoſe on</hi> others, and that he is not <hi>impertinently impos'd on</hi> himſelf: For the bare reading of an allow'd Maxim, is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly throwing away thoſe Minutes which an <hi>Heathen</hi> reckons to be highly culpable<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Exordium Juſtini ad Antoninum Imperatorem.</note> ; <hi>Otii mei reddendam rationem Cato putat.</hi> He might very well bluſh to hear <hi>Veſpatian</hi> tell him, <hi>Amici! diem perdidi.</hi> For it is not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, but to perform; not to know, but exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute; not to read, but practice, which one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34357:20"/>can be properly call'd a Man for; the <hi>former</hi> being but the <hi>Shell,</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> the <hi>Kernel.</hi> And as that <hi>Lethargick Soul</hi> muſt of neceſſity lie wholly fallow that reads not at all, ſo it muſt be naturally conſequential, that he that does, and exerts not himſelf according to its authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Dictates, and vigorouſly proſecute that <hi>knowledge</hi> into <hi>Action,</hi> lies under an extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant want of being <hi>manur'd,</hi> and can be taken no otherwiſe than a <hi>Contemplative Blockhead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well then! As 'tis plain that ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> knows what to do, ſo alſo is it as plain that he does it too; and that this may infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly appear, I ſhall briefly inſtance in the great regard he has to (that contemn'd, and almoſt loſt thing call'd) <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which he hourly demonſtrates towards
<list>
                     <item>(1) <hi>The KING.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(2) <hi>The S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BJECT.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>He exerciſes the <hi>firſt</hi> in a continu'd and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaken Fidelity, on which as neither <hi>Affection</hi> can prevail, ſo neither muſt <hi>Malice</hi> (which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally attends Mankind) attempt an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in him: For (abſtracting the guilt of that helliſh Vice call'd Perjury) the very baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; of the Action, and thoughts of being guilty of abhor'd Ingratitude, (which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to be the very Epitome of all other Crimes) ſufficiently terrifies him: For as he very well conſiders with what deteſtable Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34357:20"/>
                  <hi>Humphrey Baniſter</hi> lies, for betraying the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> notwithſtanding the many Favours the <hi>Duke</hi> had confer'd on <hi>him,</hi> and his Proteſtations of concealing <hi>him.</hi> So he alſo very well knows what <hi>Trophies,</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalizing Fame</hi> attend the Aſhes of <hi>Hubert Burgh</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Baker's Chronicle <hi>in King</hi> John.</note> , who was Governor of <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle to King <hi>John,</hi> when <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France</hi> came to ſtorm it, and take the Town; who finding it difficult to be done by Foree, he ſent a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to <hi>Hubert,</hi> whoſe Brother <hi>Thomas</hi> he had a little before taken <hi>Priſoner,</hi> that unleſs he would ſurrender the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> he ſhould preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee his Brother <hi>Thomas</hi> put to death with exquiſite Torments before his eyes: But this Threatning moved not the Fidelity of <hi>Hubert</hi> at all, who more regarded his Truſt, than his Brother's Life. Then <hi>Lewis</hi> ſent again, offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him a great Sum of Money; neither did this move him, for he had reſolv'd to preſerve his Loyalty as inexpugnable as his Caſtle.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Fidelity</hi> our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> boaſts of in his Duty, implies alſo an induſtrious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of it; for he is very well ſatisfied, that to be <hi>Faithful,</hi> and not <hi>Diligent,</hi> is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction: For though a Man may be <hi>honeſt</hi> in all he does, yet he is not <hi>honeſt</hi> for not doing <hi>all,</hi> and conſequently by his falling ſhort of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly performing his Duty, he lies under
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34357:21"/>the indelible Character of being <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt;</hi> and he knows that though others may command their <hi>Time,</hi> it being, as they call it, their own; yet he is ſatisfied he cannot, in regard he is paid for it, and conſequently becomes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptable.</p>
               <p>Beſides, he is not ignorant what <hi>Plautus</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures him of, (for if he had, he muſt not have ever pretended to the Name he bears) <hi>Qui è nuce nucleum eſſe vult, ſrangit nucem;</hi> there is no <hi>Sweet</hi> without its <hi>Sweal;</hi> no <hi>Gain</hi> without <hi>Pain;</hi> he muſt <hi>crack the Nut,</hi> that will <hi>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Kernel.</hi> And alſo what eternal Scandal the <hi>Greeks</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Seneca</hi> bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. vir.</note> lie under by <hi>Seneca,</hi> that ſpent their time in ſuch unprofitable, as well as impertinent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, as, <hi>How many Rowers</hi> Ulyſſes <hi>had? Which</hi> Homer <hi>writ firſt, his</hi> Iliads <hi>or</hi> Odyſſes? So that they ſpent their Lives laboriouſly in doing nothing, their Conceits being ſuch, that if they kept them to themſelves they could yield them no Fruit; and if they publiſh'd them to others, they would only appear more learnedly troubleſom: Or, as <hi>Terence</hi> upbraids them with <hi>Quid? Credis dormienti haec tibi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecturos Deos?</hi> Do you think to lie in Bed, and have your work done?</p>
               <p>To be ſhort; He concludes that theſe are Leſſons adapted only for thoſe who are ſubject
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34357:21"/>to the <hi>Ferula,</hi> or <hi>Men</hi> much more <hi>ignorant,</hi> and conſequently may be tolerable in <hi>them,</hi> but in <hi>him</hi> it would be altogether unpardonable: For as ſome Men have ſin'd in the Principles of <hi>Humanity,</hi> and muſt anſwer for not being Men, ſo he offends if he be not more; <hi>Magis extra vitia, quam cum virtutibus</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>Browns</hi> Vulg. Err.</note> ; No <hi>Luſtre</hi> is expected from the <hi>minor Stars:</hi> but if the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhould not <hi>illuminate,</hi> it were a Sin in Nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:34357:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>HAving thus far conſider'd our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> as a <hi>Servant,</hi> let us now take a ſhort Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of him as a <hi>Subject,</hi> and here we ſhall find him an abſolute Enemy to the talking (the a great Lover) of the <hi>Government;</hi> For <hi>he</hi> knows the <hi>Perſons</hi> as well as the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> to be Sacred, and are not to be cenſur'd by every <hi>Inſect,</hi> that crawls only by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their Rays, they being that <hi>Primum Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile</hi> that wholy occaſions the <hi>moving</hi> of <hi>all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Beings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He knows it to be nice and Dangerous to think (much more talk) <hi>meanly</hi> of theſe <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deities,</hi> ſince they are <hi>ſiſted</hi> from that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Bran</hi> that wholy <hi>moulds</hi> up other Mortals; He is poſitive in the Excellency of the advice a <hi>Gentleman</hi> gave when <hi>Priſoner</hi> for not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, <hi>Vincula da Linguae, vel tibi Lingua da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quae ſupra nos nihil ad nos,</hi> is of a long ſtanding, and although ſpoken by an <hi>Heathen,</hi> yet its obſervation had ſav'd many <hi>Chriſtian beads;</hi> he has read <hi>Suetonius,</hi> and from thence tells you, that in the Reign of <hi>Tiberius Nero Caeſar,</hi> a certain <hi>Droll,</hi> ſeeing a Corps paſſing by to Burial, he ſtop'd the Hearſe, and lifting
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34357:22"/>up the Dead Body, deſired him to tell <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus,</hi> that the Legacies which he left the People were not yet paid; Whereupon <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> commanded him to be brought, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paid him his due, Executed him immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, and deſired him to tell <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſo himſelf.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the Perſons and Actions of Kings are not to be jeſted with, ſince Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is the inevitable Conſequent, which his continu'd obſervation of the madneſs and folly of it in others, has fully covinc'd him off: <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer Sapit, qui alieno periculo Sapit:</hi> The beſt way of buying Wit, is with other Mens Money: He is ſatisfied the <hi>Countrey Man</hi> was very much in the right in the following Story.</p>
               <p>A Perſon of Quality walking the Fields, and ſtaying too long, a conſiderable Freſh increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Brook (which he was neceſſitated to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs) beyond its wonted Limits, and obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Plowman</hi> in the adjacent Field, call'd for the aſſiſtance of his Horſe. Upon which the <hi>Plowman</hi> approach'd, and demanded what he was? The <hi>Gentleman</hi> reply'd, He was Sir <hi>H. W.</hi> And what more? reply'd the <hi>Ruſtick,</hi> The <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſubjoin'd, That he was Juſtice of the Peace, Deputy-Lieutenant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And what elſe? ſays our <hi>Countryman.</hi> Why, in ſhort, ſays the <hi>Gentleman,</hi> I am alſo <hi>Parliament-Man for the County.</hi> Oh! Are you ſo, (ſays the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34357:23"/>
                  <hi>Plowman</hi>) then you ſhall ſtay there for me; <hi>For I will have nothing to do with State-Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> is wholly ſatisfied in relation to the Government in general, ſo has he full Contentment under his preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in particular; and thankfully em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces whatever his Superiors ſuppoſe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for him. And indeed there is a neceſſity in a Man of Prudence for it; for though wee'l allow <hi>Merit</hi> ought, yet is it altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it ſhould always meet <hi>Preferment:</hi> For as 'tis an allow'd Axiom, <hi>Fortuitum eſt naſci à Principibus;</hi> ſo is it here, he having (as is before mentioned) nothing but his <hi>Critical Minute</hi> for it. Beſides, the Numbers in this Age are extravagantly numerous that lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Equality, and thoſe of <hi>Places</hi> are no way anſwerable to thoſe of the <hi>Perſons</hi> meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly pretending to them; ſo that for him to repine, (who has already attain'd a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Form in it) would make him beyond the degree of Ridiculous.</p>
               <p>Again, We cannot allow of every <hi>Perſon</hi> that thinks himſelf deſerving, to be in reality ſo; for though in the <hi>Sphere</hi> he at preſent moves in, he does it with an allow'd Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, yet ſince none is ſo ignorant but knows, that there is a conſiderable difference between <hi>Ruling</hi> and <hi>Obeying,</hi> the <hi>former</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a total alteration of the Man from what
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34357:23"/>he was when the latter; which his <hi>Superiors</hi> being ſenſible of, (who are much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judges of <hi>Him,</hi> than <hi>Himſelf</hi>) poſſibly at preſent think it not for his <hi>Advantage;</hi> hence is it that many <hi>ingenious Men</hi> meet with a <hi>Stet.</hi> But our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> never thinks of Advancement 'till his <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> do, and receives it then with an <hi>Ex Mero Motu;</hi> and if they ſhould, his chiefeſt Ambition is to climb up to their good Opinion, on which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he values himſelf: So that he is not intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with that ambitious Madneſs, as to covet that which he is no way capable of perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Or, with <hi>Phaeton,</hi> rather hazard the burning of the whole World, than miſs the gratifying his wild and irrational Inclinations. He knows <hi>Solon,</hi> one of the wiſe men of <hi>Greece,</hi> complains of a young Nobleman of <hi>Athens,</hi> That if he could but have pluck'd out of his Head the worm of Ambition, and heal him of his greedy deſire to Rule, that then there could not be a Man of greater Virtue than he.</p>
               <p>And as he is not <hi>Ambitiouſly inclin'd,</hi> much leſs is he guilty of <hi>Envying</hi> the good Fortune of others; nay, though poſſibly, leſs deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than himſelf. <hi>Envy</hi> is defin'd by ſome to be the hatred of another's felicity in reſpect of Superiors, becauſe they are not equal to them; in reſpect of Inferiors, leſt they ſhould be equal to them; and in reſpect of Equals, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are equal to them: but our <hi>Exciſe-Man,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34357:24"/>Sorte ſue contentus,</hi> envies none of their <hi>Places,</hi> but their <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Virtues;</hi> of which notwithſtanding he becomes a daily <hi>Emulator;</hi> and in all other things he follows the Advices of the <hi>Poet,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Contented is he with his Lot,</l>
                  <l>What others have, he covets not.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But laſtly, (which indeed is high time to come to) he feeds not himſelf up with that which is highly <hi>improbable,</hi> if not altogether <hi>impoſſible</hi> to come to paſs; and indeed it would make <hi>Heraclitus</hi> himſelf burſt, to obſerve what ridiculous Fancies ſome perſons enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of their future Grandeur, when the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of it is no otherwiſe grounded, than that of the <hi>poor Prieſt's,</hi> who being asked why he was going to <hi>Rome</hi> from his own Countrey? Reply'd, It was becauſe the <hi>Pope</hi> being dead, he did not know but that he might be choſen <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:34357:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>HIther to have we (with all the Brevity we were capable of expreſſing) conſider'd our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> Behaviour, in relation to the <hi>KING;</hi> let us now take a ſhort Survey of that reſpecting the Subject, and that
<list>
                     <item>Firſt, To thoſe under his Inſpection.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, To thoſe who are not.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, Concerning thoſe under his Inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I ſhall briefly inſinuate, That our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> being aſſur'd, that as Juſtice is painted without <hi>Eyes,</hi> to demonſtrate that ſhe never makes any diſtinction of Perſons, ſo (as he has read out of <hi>Quintilian</hi>) he knows there were ſeveral Images of Judges erected in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> without <hi>Hands,</hi> to ſhew that they ſhould not be corrupted with<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Vid. Godwin.</note> 
                  <hi>Bribes.</hi> The <hi>firſt,</hi> he is ſenſible is prejudice to the Perſon offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the <hi>ſecond</hi> to himſelf, unjuſt in taking, and both <hi>Perjury</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">In juſtitiae paena comes.</note> in performing; which Conſideration has ſuch a powerful Influence over him, that he is even ſhy of a <hi>Familiarity:</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:34357:25"/>For though <hi>Humanity</hi> obliges him to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Reſpect, yet <hi>Prudence</hi> denies an <hi>Intimacy;</hi> the Cenſure of the World being now arriv'd to that extravagant pitch, as to draw poſitive Concluſions from very uncertain Premiſes. I mean a bare word, a confirmation of its reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though indifferent in its intention. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he knows if he ſhould once prove falſe, (as he highly muſt if thus guilty) the odds are very unequal, but they will too; that lie not under ſuch invincible Obligations: ſo that if that Theological Maxim<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Male partum male diſperit.</note> , That things wrongfully got, have a very uncertain Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, convinces him not; yet that Political one of <hi>Seneca</hi> is abſolutely prevalent, That it is a great Fault to believe every one, and a great one too to truſt <hi>One</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Credendum nec omni, nec nulli.</note> , which makes him in this Caſe to acquieſce with <hi>Chaucer,</hi> when he tells us,
<q>
                     <l>— As Proverbs do ſay,</l>
                     <l>Three may keep Counſel, if Twain be away.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For ſince he knows the generality of Mankind frequently verify the Adage of <hi>Alterâ ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u fert lapidem, panem oſtendit alterâ,</hi> he is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to follow our Poet's advice,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34357:25"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>— Hic murus aheneus eſto</l>
                     <l>Nil conſcire ſibi, nullâ palleſcere culpâ. <hi>Hor.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, As our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> is not <hi>Rigorous,</hi> ſo is he not <hi>Timerous</hi> in the execution of his Office: The <hi>firſt</hi> intimating an immoderate Severity, the <hi>laſt</hi> a bale<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Degeneres animos timor arguit.</note> Puſillanimity. He is not to be biaſs'd by his excited Paſſions, nor hector'd by Affronts and Clamor. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders the Loſer, claims the priviledge of <hi>Speaking,</hi> but not of <hi>Prating.</hi> He allows their asking Queſtions moderately, but not making Solutions ſcandalouſly: Such Perſons ever cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all things into queſtion, but are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of approving any thing; which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration leads him to the remembrance of the Adage, That he that will allow himſelf to be a <hi>Sheep,</hi> muſt alſo allow himſelf to be eaten by the <hi>Wolves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would not be here miſtaken, as if our <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe-Man</hi> ſhould be guilty of opprobrious and railing Terms, generally predominant, No; But he either moderately convinces them with the ſevereſt Scrutinies of Reaſon, or (to thoſe not ſuſceptible of ſuch) anſwers them with <hi>Silence.</hi> He knows ſuch Language be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes only <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> and not any there,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34357:26"/>but the <hi>weaker Sex.</hi> He concludes it very much beneath a Man (much more an <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi>) to be guilty of ſuch ſcandalous Actions, ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagantly contradictory to thoſe common Rules of Civility, he is ſo ſtrictly charg'd, as well as deſires to be obſervant of. He is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd thoſe who offer ſuch baſe Scurrility, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear abſolute Reprobates to every thing that can be call'd modeſt or good, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpenſe with each Action that exhibits the Epithet of Scandalons. He is poſitive the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcerning Crew,</hi> being uncapable of ſatisfaction in rational Anſwers, he will give them none at all: ſo that though he cannot deny but it muſt adminiſter diſturbance to the <hi>Giver,</hi> yet he is reſolv'd it ſhall not to the <hi>Receiver:</hi> And when an Injury is done him, and 'tis not in his power to revenge himſelf of it, <hi>he then diſſembles, and takes no notice of it; but when it is, he generouſly forgives it.</hi> He remembers the Story of the Earl of <hi>Carnarvan,</hi> who being in a Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fee-houſe, and accidentally falling into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with a Doctor of Phyſick, the Doctor told him he ly'd; The Earl, though a Perſon of much Honour and Courage, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any offence at it, mildly reply'd, <hi>Doctor, I had rather take the Lye of you a thouſand times, than Phyſick once.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And alſo that of Biſhop <hi>Cooper,</hi> who having a froward Wife, leſt her Husband ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice his health by his over-much Study, when he was compiling his famous Dictionary, one
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34357:26"/>day (in his abſence) got into his Study, and took all the Notes he had been gathering in eight years, and burnt them; where of when ſhe had acquainted him, he only ſaid, <hi>Woman, thou haſt put me to eight years ſtudy more.</hi> So that he is reſolv'd that nothing ſhall interrupt that Current of Courteſy and Civility he at firſt imblb'd, which he knows, is not punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of Behaviour; I mean, that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in certain modiſh and particular Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Faſhions in Cloaths, Geſture, Meen, Speech, or the like, is not uſing ſuch Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Words, Phraſes, Studies, Opinions, Games, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as are in faſhion in Court with Gailants, Ladies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this is a conſtrain'd Formality, not Civility; a complying with the Times, not with Perſons; and varieth with the Age or Seaſon frequently, according to the Fancy of mechanick Perſons in their ſeveral Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: whereas the Rules of Civility, founded upon Prudence and Charity, are to Perpetuity unchangeable; and conſiſts<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Vid. Ob. on Education, <hi>222.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in not expreſſing by Actions or Speeches any Injury, Diſeſteem, Offence, or undervaluing of any other, in being ready to do all good Offices, and ordinary kindneſs for another, and receiving no Injuries or Offences from others,</hi> i. e. <hi>in not reſenting every Word or Action, which may (perhaps rationally) be interpreted to be Diſ ſteem or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndervaluing.</hi> But,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34357:27"/>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Jam fatis eſt — ne me Criſpini ſcrinia Lippi</l>
                        <l>Compilaſſe putes, verbum non ampliùs addam. <hi>Horace.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But 'tis enough — leſt you ſhould think that mine</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Are</hi> Holland's <hi>Volumns, I'le not add a Line.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:34357:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>BUT to return: As our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> truſts them not with a <hi>Secret,</hi> ſo dare he not to venture them in relation to their <hi>Occupation;</hi> for <hi>Concealments</hi> are as natural to a <hi>Retailer,</hi> as a <hi>Cittern</hi> is to a <hi>Barber,</hi> or <hi>Burnt-Brandy</hi> to <hi>Madam B</hi>— which rather than miſs, he would hazard the <hi>Plagues of Europe,</hi> or (which is the ſame thing) the mercy of the <hi>French</hi> King: And, I preſume, it would be no Sole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm, or (I was going to ſay) an Affront, to affirm them terms Synonimous, they ever reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning it no breach of the <hi>Principles of Honeſty</hi> to cheat the <hi>Exciſe-Man,</hi> but rather a <hi>Duty incumbent</hi> to ſecure that which they call their <hi>own.</hi> The reſult of this <hi>Conſideration</hi> exerts his diligence, and conſequently concludes, <hi>Qui quaerit inveniet,</hi> He that will have an Hare for Supper, muſt hunt in the morning. He knows Labour and Diligence to be the Miſtreſſes of all commendable Arts, without which, none ever yet arriv'd to any Character in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth that may be call'd conſiderable. <hi>Scaliger</hi> and <hi>Aquinus</hi> (two the moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Pillars and Standards of Learning in the Univerſe) never got that conſiderable Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, but by Watching and Labour. And <hi>Croeſus</hi> himſelf got not his Riches by lying
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34357:28"/>ſtill. Nay, it gives a great addition to its ſweetneſs; for as Hunger is the beſt Sawce, ſo Labour creates the beſt Palate.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— <hi>Tu pulmentaria quare</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sudando</hi> —</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— Any Meat</l>
                     <l>Is Ven'ſon if obtain'd by Sweat.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Or (I beg pardon, but cannot avoid it) the conſideration of the Ant's diligence, is no ſmall Incitement to him, thus deſcrib'd by <hi>Horace,</hi> Lib. 1. Ser. 1.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— <hi>Sicut</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Parvula (nam Exemplo eſt) magni Formica laboris</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ore trahit quodcunque poteſt, atque addit acervo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quem ſtruit, haud ignara ac non ineauta futuri.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Thus Engliſh'd by Mr. <hi>Brome.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Juſt like the Ant, (for that's their Pattorn) ſmall</l>
                     <l>In bulk, but great in thrift, who draws in all</l>
                     <l>That e're ſhe can, and adds it to her ſtore;</l>
                     <l>Which ſhe foreſeeing Want had heap'd before,</l>
                     <l>And in the Rage of Winter keeps within,</l>
                     <l>To feed on what her Providence laid in.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>It is obſerv'd by the <hi>Naturaliſts,</hi> that <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra nihil fecit fruſtra,</hi> and from thence Dr.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34357:28"/>
                  <hi>Brow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulg. Errors.</note> contradicts the common Notion of the <hi>Camelion's</hi> living by the Air; for to what purpoſe ſhould that Animal be by Nature ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli'd with Guts, Stomach and Tongue, if it fed upon that Airy Aliment which has not a neceſſity of, or indeed an occaſion for, them? So to what purpoſe ſhould ſhe have deliver'd a Soul into the Body which hath Arms and Legs, (only Inſtruments of Action) but becauſe it was intended the Mind ſhould make uſe of and employ them; and though <hi>Atlas</hi> has the whole World in poſſeſſion, yet is he oblig'd to bear it too.</p>
               <p>Another Inducement our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> has for exerciſing this Induſtry, is what he has read in <hi>Plautus, Videte quaeſo, quid poteſt pecunia! Aſſem habeas aſſem valeas;</hi> He knows a Man ſhall be valu'd and eſteem'd according to what he hath. He hath read the Story of one of the Emperors of <hi>Turkie,</hi> when ſome of his Flatterers attempting to make him believe his Beard commànded Adoration, and was worth the World. Upon which (to demonſtrate the Almighty Power of Money) he commanded it to be ſhav'd, and ſent to the Market with this Proclamation, That the Grand Signior's Beard was expos'd to a Barter; but (as the Hiſtorian tells us) it went not ſo far as a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and would not buy a Pound of Meat. I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34357:29"/>cannot avoid <hi>Horace</hi>'s account of its force, and if you'l forgive me this once, I can aſſure you I have almoſt done with my Fragments of Latin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— <hi>Omnis enim Res,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Virtus, fama, decus, divina humanaque pulchris</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Divitiis parent: quas qui conſtruxerit, ille</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clarus erit, fortis, Juſtus, Sapiens, etiam &amp; Rex,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et quicquid volet.</hi> —</l>
                     <l>Horace, lib. 2. ſat. 3.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For every thing, <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane</hi> too,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Virtue, Wit, Comelineſs,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> do</l>
                     <l>Submit their Necks to <hi>Riches</hi> ſplendid Sway;</l>
                     <l>Which whoſoever heaps together, may</l>
                     <l>Be <hi>Noble, Valiant, Juſt,</hi> and <hi>Wiſe,</hi> nay <hi>King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or (if 'twere poſſible) an higher thing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>A third Encouragement for our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> Diligence, is the Conſideration of the Mutability of all Sublunary Affairs, and ſince no Mortal is ſo firmly fix'd but may (nay fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently does) meet with Viciſſitudes, he is certain of a much more uncertainty: For though that wheeling Goddeſs is not unſitly compar'd to the Moon, in her variety of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributions to all, yet to him ſhe is ever in her laſt Quarter, immediately ready for her wonted Change. Publick Places having many Mutations incident to them, which miſs all other ways of living, and conſequently he waits in a continual expectation of it. And
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34357:29"/>as he remembers the Advice of <hi>Juvenal</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Vulgus ſequitur Fortunam &amp; odit damnatos. —</note> , If once a Man falls, all will down with him; ſo is he not ignorant of the Advice of <hi>Henry the Great</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> when having promoted a Perſon of low degree to be Chancellor, who thereupon had his own lively <hi>Effigies</hi> (made in a curious piece of <hi>Arras</hi> Hangings) ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the uppermoſt part of Fortune's Wheel, which he having ſhewed the King, <hi>You would do well,</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>to pin the Wheel faſt, leſt it ſhould turn again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This foreſight of his Diſcharge, is no ſmall Spur to him for the laying up an honeſt Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt it, and therefore is not unmindful of the Adages, That as 'tis<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Mus non uni ſides antro — <hi>Eraſ.</hi>
                  </note> good to have two Strings to one's Bowe, ſo is it alſo to make<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Non ſemper erunt Saturnalia. <hi>Sen.</hi>
                  </note> Hay while the Sun ſhines. But there is a further Conſideration that obliges him to an indefatigable Diligence; for if Poverty drowns the moſt towering parts, and makes even Youth<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Nil habet infoelix paupertas du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius in ſe Quam quod ridiculos komines faeit.</note> ridiculous, it muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity follow, that it muſt be the very abſtract of all Misfortunes, when accompanied with Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and old Age, he being then arriv'd to his <hi>Ne plus ultra,</hi> and conſequently to an impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34357:30"/>of recovering his neglected Minutes. And he knows that ſince all Men are not born under thoſe fortunate Planets, as to have a Competency procured for them, he is reſolv'd creditably to ſecure one, before the vigor of his Youth ſhall meet with an abatement, this being his only Harveſt time, which he muſt wholly depend on in the Winter of his Age; and in regard he remembers it a common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, That a young Serving-man is generally an old Beggar; he ſleeps not without joining with the Opinion of <hi>Horace:</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ille gravem duro terram qui vertit aratro:</l>
                  <l>Perfidus hic caupo, Miles, Nautaeque per omne</l>
                  <l>Audaces Mare qui currunt: hac mente laborem</l>
                  <l>Seſe ſerre, ſenes ut in Oria tuta recedant,</l>
                  <l>Aiunt, quum tibi ſunt congeſta cibaria—</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hor. Ser. 1.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Thus Engliſhed by Mr. <hi>Creech</hi>—as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The Soldier ſights, the buſy Tradeſman cheats,</l>
                  <l>And finds a thouſand tricks, and choice deceits.</l>
                  <l>The heavy Plow contents the labouring Hind,</l>
                  <l>The Merchant ſtrives with ev'ry tide and wind;</l>
                  <l>And all this Toil to get vaſt heaps of Gold,</l>
                  <l>That they may live at eaſe when they are old.</l>
                  <l>When they have gotten ſtore for numerous Years,</l>
                  <l>They may be free from Want, and from its Fears.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:34357:30"/>
               <p>Theſe are ſome of thoſe prevailing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which induce our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> diligent performance of his Duty; and not queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but the meaneſt Capacity apprehends that by that word, I mean a faithful execution of it, as is inſtanc'd before; I ſhail not trouble the Reader with Repetitions, but ſhall deſcend to the laſt as well as chiefeſt Argument in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and that is, that his great Maſter (to whom he is reſponſible for his well-being) is not defrauded; and though the former Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may in ſome ſenſe be allowable, yet they cannot in the ſtrict Rules of Probity, unleſs they meet conjunctively with this. 'Tis He only allows him that Competency he enjoys, by a frugal management of which, he may not only live without any other dependance, but<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Adde pdrum parvo magnus accrwus eris.</note> ſecure an <hi>Aſylum</hi> for futurity. And it would certainly be the higheſt piece of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude (than which the Heathens<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Ingratum dixeris &amp; omnia dixiſti.</note> reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd nothing worſe) in him, if he made not this his chiefeſt Aim and Reſolution, ſince <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratus, qui beneficium accepiſſe ſe negat quod ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit; Ingratus, qui id diſſimulat; rurſum Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, qui non reddit: at omnium Ingratiſſimus eſt qui oblitus eſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:34357:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>Since then our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> is ſatisfied, that the generality of Mankind (I mean thoſe conſtant Defrauders) are what <hi>Aexander</hi> was wont to ſay of <hi>Antipater,</hi> That outwardly he did wear a white Garment, but that it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways lined with Purple; that is, fair in their Speech, but foul in their Actions. It follows then, as a natural reſult of the Premiſes, that he only things of eaſe, but works on; and though it may be his chance to ſucceed Induſtry it ſelf, he concludes not therefore that they ought to be confided in, ſince he knows no Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhaves ſo cloſe, but another may find ſome work. Neither ſhall the conſideration of their having often commuted for it, be any <hi>Remora</hi> to his Search, they having another Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion too, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome hopes of retreiving their former Loſſes, by continu'd Fallacies. Nay, though their refunding has been ſucceeded with ſufficient Admonitions of forbearing the like Practices, yet they will not, or cannot hear, the former for the precited Reaſon, and the latter (I mean ſtill among thoſe common Cheats) for that of the <hi>Epigramatiſt:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Non potis eſt Proclus digitis emungere Naſum</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Namque eſt pro Naſi mole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>uſilla marus:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:34357:31"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Non vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ille Jovem ſternutans, quippe nec audit</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sternu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> mentum tam procul aure ſonat.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Proclus</hi> with's Hand his Noſe can never wipe,</l>
                        <l>His Hand too little is his Noſe to gripe:</l>
                        <l>He ſneezing calls not <hi>Jove,</hi> for why he hears</l>
                        <l>Himſelf not ſneeze, the found's ſo far from's Ears.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Being thus reſolv'd, he embraces every Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, and lets not any thing miſs him for want of Circumſpection and Care. He is watchful to an Exceſs; and if he ſleep, it is as the Naturaliſts obſerve of the Hare, <hi>i. e.</hi> with his Eyes open; for he always conſiders, that Foxes when ſleeping have nothing fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their mouths.</p>
               <p>He is ſatisfied this alone will not be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prevalent, and therefore has ever an Aſſiſtant <hi>incognito,</hi> which he never diſcevers but when neceſſitated; and he knows it a great piece of Imprudence, (<hi>Quid non mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali pectora cogis Auri</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Virg,</note> 
                  <hi>ſacra ſames?</hi>) as well as Ingratitude, not to return a ſuitable encouragement; for he that gives thee a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, ought to have a Leg and a Wing. But though he diſputes not the frequent occaſion of it, yet he knows there is not a continual neceſſity, and therefore its allowance is agreed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34357:32"/>on with Reſtrictions: For notwithſtanding two Eyes is ſaid to ſee better than one, yet he had rather (conſidering the predo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inant Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, eſpecially in relation to an <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> Secrets) truſt one of his own, than thrice the number that are not, if with a poſſibility it can be perform'd without them; and ever remembers the Rule, That what thou sanſt do thy ſelf, rely not on another.</p>
               <p>Our Sinner being thus detected, has made himſelf ſubject to the offended Law, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to the mercy of our Officer, who has ever a great regard to diſtinguiſh between the Circumſtances of the Perſon and Offence: This he makes his chiefeſt ſtudy, he ever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it an eſteem'd Qualification. He knows Compaſſion a natural Attendant on Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and it would be wholly unpardonable in him (who ought to be a leading Example of it) not to give an unqueſtion'd Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it upon every neceſſitated Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. He allows it inſignificant, to offer at a Supply from thoſe, who have a daily occaſion of begging one He owns it ridiculous, to ſtruggle for ſatisfaction from thoſe who cannot give it their own Belly. He is ſatisfi'd it is highly culpable, warrantably to ſink thoſe who are already cruſht, or to offer the making himſelf fat, by their lean and inconſiderable Incomes. He concludes it very impertinent, to patch up his Fortunes from thoſe, who, to his hand, are out at heels, or to cover himſelf
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34357:32"/>with their Nakedneſs. He denies not but that Cruelty is the rigorous effect of an evil-diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Will, and the Fruit which is reap'd from Injuſtice: And if it is dormant in the canker'd Breaſt, he is reſolv'd it ſhall not in his that is ſound. He confeſſes the Offender has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a Fault, and he acknowledges he ſhould commit a greater in not extenuating the Mulct: And that it is equally ſcandalous to expect Impoſſibilities, I mean, from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer in making, and the latter in expecting Reparation. He has read, That the moſt Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble Beaſt is ever the moſt Cruel; and that the Noble Lyon paſſes by that ſubmiſſive Prey, which the unpitying Tyger unmercifully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys. The frequent Obſervation of this in others, is ſufficient to make any but him an abſolute <hi>Pythagorian,</hi> and allow a <hi>Metempſychoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of <hi>Panther's</hi> Souls into the Bodies of much more cruel Men: Theſe he abominates, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will totally abandon, ſince they are not adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have an humane Compoſition.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>For Veins of Flint are everywh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e diſperſt,</l>
                  <l>In ſlender Branches thro his Iron Breaſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Or, as <hi>Withers</hi> puns it:
<q>
                     <l>No Kind ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkind to their Kind we find</l>
                     <l>As Mankind unto Mankind is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkind.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Yet he knows too, that that which cannot be made into Butter, may be made into Cheeſe:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34357:33"/>But ſince 'tis ever allow'd, that it is as great Cruelty to ſpare all, as to ſpare none, our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> is reſolv'd upon his former Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that therefore the Capable are not to be thrown into an immediate Oblivion, knowing that thereby he would wholly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the very intention of the Law, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits Fines, Penalties and Forfeitures <hi>in Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; Inops Aadacia tuta eſt,</hi> having no rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him, and will therefore prove a vain and ſucceſsle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Excuſe: For notwithſtanding the Law pardons the Poor, (that is tacitly, becauſe they have nothing) yet it does not therefore follow that it ſhould forgive the Rich, or thoſe who have enough, it falling not under the Rules of Charity or Compaſſion, to an exact obſervation of which, our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> lies under an indiſpenſible Obligation. Beſides, he ſuppoſes it equally Criminal to hurt the Innocent, and to let the Nocent go free, where there is ſomething conveniently to be ſpar'd. He that dances muſt pay the Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and he that conceals muſt produce. He that mixe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt pay for it, and then no doubt will be witty, beyond the aſſiſtance of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> or <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſince Wit bought is better than Wit taught; ſo that as he that confeſſes may be hang'd, ſo he that denies muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:34357:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>HAving given you ſome few of thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks I have made on our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> Behaviour towards thoſe under his Inſpection; I come now to inſtance his Demeanor towards thoſe who are not, which ought to be parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culariz'd in a treble Capacity, <hi>viz.</hi> to his <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, Equals</hi> and <hi>Inferiors:</hi> But in regard this would occaſion a Volume alone, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſwell beyond the intended Brevity of theſe Papers; and ſince alſo many of theſe Obſervations would interfere with thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready deliver'd, I ſhall refer the Reader to the numerous Books on that Subject, eſpecially that Compleat Tract of Education of Young Gentlemen<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Printed at the Theatre.</note> , (which is our <hi>Exeiſe-Man's</hi> admir'd and inſeparable <hi>Vade Mecum</hi>) and content my ſelf with the bare hinting ſome few he lies under a neceſſity of obſerving, <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus</hi> an <hi>Exciſe-Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let Fortune throw him into what Company ſoever, he is ſure not to be profane; he knows it Capital to reflect on Earthly Majeſty, and to have mean apprehenſions, much more
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34357:34"/>expreſſions, of that tremendous Arbiter and Diſpoſer of us his ſpeaking Worms, that can with the ſame eaſe reduce them to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Chaos, as he then allow'd them a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. I ſay he is ſatisfied, that he who thinks there can be no Jeſt, without the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Oath, and conſequently the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning his Name, who, in a minute, may caſt the whole Creation in an Ague-fit, is far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the aſſiſtance of <hi>Helebore</hi> it ſelf, it being a certain Indication of a confirm'd madneſs: And inſtead of the <hi>Exciſe,</hi> is fit only to be an Inhabitant of <hi>Poneropolis,</hi> a City built by<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Plut. <hi>Mor.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who having aſſembled the moſt profligate Wretches, and thoſe whom he imagin'd beyond the reach of Admonition, put them into this City which he built on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and call'd it <hi>the City of the Profane.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Proverb ſays, <hi>Tell me his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and I'll tell you the Man;</hi> his choice is ever for the beſt: For he knows, that as the Profane can only aſſiſt him in his Damnation, ſo the Poor can never help him at all; and he concludes, that as either of them are to be avoided, ſo is alſo the Company of Fools, who can be no way ſerviceable towards the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of his Intellectuals, which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes to be the deſign'd Origin of Society. And although his Place may inevitably caſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34357:34"/>him amongſt them, yet he is ever upon his Guard, and, with the <hi>Perſians,</hi> fights flying; and indeed there ſeems a neceſſity of his being well arm'd, to clear himſelf of the greateſt part of the World's Compoſition; and it is his whole ſtudy to make himſelf a Separatiſt herein, for he knows in relation to the firſt, that Contamination is an infallible Incident, ſince the defil'd Fly that feeds on dung, has ever its correſpondent colour. To the ſecond he is ſatisfied againſt ordinary Company, ſince the meanneſs of the Commodity makes it for every Bodies money. And in reſpect to the laſt, he concludes, that as it is no advancement of his Qualifications, ſo muſt it of neceſſity immerge thoſe he was ſo happy in before, Scandal and Infamy being its inſeparate At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant; nay, he is ſatisfied out of <hi>Seneca,</hi> 'Tis only keeping Childrens company, who will never arrive to Mens eſtate, <hi>Nam inter ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera mala hoc quoque habet ſtultitia, ſemper incipit vivere—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He is very ſenſible of the Deference payable to thoſe who move in an <hi>uncommon Sphere,</hi> and though in ſtrictneſs he may imagine he does, yet he is not ſo extravagantly Ignorant, as to ſuppoſe his Intimacy with the Gentlemen of the Countrey wherein he is ſent (which is wholly occaſion'd by their Condeſcention) ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a parity: He is (it's true) a Gentleman by his Place, but they by Deſcent, and he knows very well that one Poſt may deſtroy
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34357:35"/>that Gentility he pretends to, whereas theirs admits of a duration equivalent with time it ſelf. He is ſatisfied it lies in the Power of his Maſters with or without Reaſon to reduce him in <hi>ſtatu quo;</hi> whereas an extenuation of their quality ſuppoſes an Impoſſibility: and that it may be palpably evident that their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances no way admit of a Competition (ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting the certainty that attends them, and the incertainty that follows him) and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that a ſubmiſſive regard is perfectly obligatory; he conſiders, That (as tis allow'd by all) it may ſometimes fall in the way of the moſt Indigent to do him a kindneſs, it muſt certainly happen often in the Power of the Rich to perform that which he will not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine altogether acceptable.</p>
               <p>And ſince this cannot admit of a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, our <hi>Exciſe-Man,</hi> of conſequence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of this Regard to be a part of Prudence as well as his Duty; for it would be an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Demonſtration of a Soul totally Eclips'd that ſhould not offer a ſuitable reſpect to thoſe who not only command it by all the Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both Sacred and Profane, but very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently proves that Tenth which gives Life and Motion to all inferior Orbs, and is the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe of the Elevation of thoſe Perſons and Parts, by a certain and progreſſive Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that have any way demonſtrated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves meritorious of it.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:34357:35"/>
               <p>Beſides, it has always been obſerv'd that an obliging ſubmiſſion and condeſcention has been ever the diſcriminating Character and Diſtinction of a Gentleman, for thoſe of the greateſt minds and beſt Extractions, are ever the moſt obliging and humble; whereas thoſe of the moſt abject Spirits are the moſt Inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Imperious; <hi>Alexander</hi> the<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Ladies Calling. 66.</note> Great, though Terrible in the Field, yet was of a gentle complaiſant Converſation. Familiarly treating thoſe about him: Yet <hi>Creſpinus, Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſus, Nymphidius,</hi> and others Enfranchiſed Bond men we find inſolently Trampling upon the <hi>Roman</hi> Senators and Conſuls. So that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Innumerable other Arguments for its obſervation, he pays it, to avoid the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of being imagin'd of the Dunghil ſtraine.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Who like ſo many Empty Pitchers may,</l>
                  <l>By the Lugg'd Ears be carried any way.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I ſay this Humility is ſo firmly fix'd in him, that he might be thought Superior to that that's Common, for he very well remembers the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory from whence he is aſſured, That this winning vertue was ſo Conſpicuous and Charming in <hi>Cincinnatus,</hi> that though he conceal'd himſelf by digging in a Garden, it ſent
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34357:36"/>him quickly thence and gave him the prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dictator.</p>
               <p>But this ſubmiſſion in his Behaviour to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors ought to be carryed much further, it being his Duty in a double capacity, for as it is required from every Perſon in general among Chriſtian as well as <hi>Ethnick</hi> Communities; he has a further obligation for the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it, I mean the Injunctions and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Commands of thoſe Commiſſioners to whom he is oblig'd for his Employment. 'Tis their reiterated orders to Demonſtrate an obliging Complacency to all, but an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecial Submiſſion to the Gentlemen they meet with in their admir'd Perambulation; Nay, this particular has been ſo often inculcated by private Orders and Printed Directions, that were we not apprehenſive of a daily neceſſity for its Remembrance, we ſhould with Submiſſion imagine it lay under the Guilt of a Repetition. This then becoms his Duty under a double Notion, the former as a Man, the latter as an Officer; and for the non-performance of the Dictates and Oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maxims of the Firſt, he will find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Diſcarded of Humane Society; and his neglecting the orders of the Laſt, will infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly Diſcharge him of that Incomparable Dependance. <hi>Nam Pericula, Labores, Dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, etiam optimus quiſque ſuſcipere mavult, quam deſerere ullam Officii partem.</hi> Cicero.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:34357:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>NOw although, as was intimated, thoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> may be ſo Condeſcending as to <hi>allow of,</hi> and <hi>encourage</hi> a <hi>Familiarity;</hi> yet our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> embraces it with a great deal of Diſcretion and Caution; which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces a poſitive Reſolution in him, that it ſhall not adminiſter an occaſion of <hi>Negligence</hi> in his Duty; to which he has a reſolute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and of which nothing ſhall create a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution. He joyfully allows of the freedom they are pleas'd to admit of, but with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd ſubſerviency to that <hi>Abſolute Neceſſarium</hi> to which he is cemented by all the prevailing Obligations imaginable, and he is then (with his uſual Submiſſion) ſubſequently <hi>Theirs.</hi> He has read <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and from him, remembers it was a remarkable Inſtance of the Prudence of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes,</hi> who going into the Regions of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Souls, would not exchange ſo much as one word with his Mother there, 'til he had firſt obtain'd an Anſwer from the Oracle, and diſpatch'd the buſineſs he came about; and then turning to her, he afforded ſome ſmall time for a few Queſtions of much leſs moment and concern. He owns the admittance to be no ſmall addition to his Reputation, but when it interferes with the Minutes he is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34357:37"/>For in relation to his Duty, he knows too, it is a great ſubſtraction from it, and which, as is prerecited, would intitle him to the indelible Character of being unjuſt.</p>
               <p>This Conſideration produces a prevailing Argument againſt immoderate <hi>Drinking,</hi> and moderate (I know not whether that Word can be allow'd) <hi>Gaming;</hi> ſince they wholly diſcompſe him for the Duties of the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent day. I ſhall not rob my <hi>Common-place Book</hi> for Precepts or Examples againſt them in relation to him, (for it is not our Concern to cenſure others) but cannot avoid the incert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what Mr. <hi>Howell</hi> tells us in relation to the <hi>firſt</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Howell</hi>'s Letters.</note> , That by the ancient Laws of <hi>Spain,</hi> if a Woman could have proved her Husband to have been thrice Drunk, ſhe might have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately pleaded it as a ſufficient Argument for a Divorce. And what St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joins, <hi>Ebrietas eſt blandus Daemon dulce venenum, ſuave peccatum; quod qui habet ſcipſum non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, quod qui facit peccatum non facit, ſed ipſe eſt peccatum—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although our <hi>Exciſe-Man,</hi> upon ſome emergent Opportunities, may be prevail'd to nibble at the <hi>former,</hi> yet he eternally ſhuns the <hi>latter;</hi> the Inconveniences that inevitably attend it being <hi>innumerable,</hi> eſpecially relating
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34357:37"/>to him, who hat neither <hi>Money</hi> or <hi>Time,</hi> to throw away upon ſuch an unaccountable and impertinent Vice; and ſhall therefore only inſiſt with what Scandal and Infamy it was branded with by the Antients (not to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether our Moderns have not had much more reaſon) as appears by the Law of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius Alexander</hi> Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Perſon ſhould be taken <hi>Gaming,</hi> ſhould be look'd on as a <hi>Recorded Frantick.</hi> as not having a competent diſcretion for Self-government: And for ſome ſuch Reaſon the Noble <hi>Cobilon</hi> being ſent to <hi>Corinth,</hi> for the obtaining a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual League and Friendſhip<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Corn. Agrip. de Van. Scien.</note> between them and the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> when he ſaw the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Senators playing at <hi>Dice,</hi> he return'd without doing any thing, ſaying, <hi>That he would not ſo much defile the Glory of the</hi> Spartans, <hi>as that it ſhould be ſaid they had made a League with Gameſters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſince theſe <hi>Vices</hi> ſeem to imply all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they being the <hi>Baſis</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> on which all imaginable Enormities raiſe their <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructure,</hi> I ſhall not mention any other, but briefly incert his Reaſons of Abhorrence againſt the laſt, which he obſerv'd out of the <hi>beſt</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Obadiah Walk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</note> 
                  <hi>Educator,</hi> and the <hi>worſt Educated</hi> he has read; and are</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:34357:38"/>
               <p>Firſt, It creates an acquaintance with low, baſe, unworthy Company.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Learning from them ſordid and unmanly Arts, as Sharking, Cheating, Lying, Equivocating, which is by them call'd Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witting.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Loſs of Time and Money.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Great engagements of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which is the moſt effectual and ſpeedy means to obliterate any good Thought, and introduce the Superiority of the Beaſtial Part.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Learning, or at leaſt patiently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during thoſe abominable Swearings, Curſings, Blaſphemings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, Danger from other Mens Paſſions, the general Reſult of Play-quarrels, being Murders, Duels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in fine, <hi>Eſt Ars Mendaciorum, Perjuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum, Furtorum, Litium, Injuriorum, Homici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diorumque Mater: &amp; eſt verè malorum Daemonum inventum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Caution our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> obſerves on the Friendſhip of his Superiors, is, That it ſhall not adminiſter an occaſion of diſcovering
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34357:38"/>a <hi>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ealment,</hi> I mean of <hi>diſcloſing a Secret;</hi> and therefore he is ſure of ever following the Rule of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> which was, to check the too early Loquacity of his Scholars, by impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on them five years ſilence from their firſt Admiſſion. And 'tis obſervable, that Nature has given us two Eyes and two Ears, and but one Tongue, (and that doubly barracadow'd by Lips and Teeth) that we might <hi>hear and ſee at leaſt twice as much as we ſpeak.</hi> He knows it would be the higheſt piece of Injuſtice to declare that, which was not only attended with an <hi>Injunction,</hi> but a promiſe too of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</hi> He finds how infamous and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous it was among the <hi>Romans,</hi> to be call'd <hi>Homo Rimarum;</hi> and particularly remembers that Heroick Anſwer of <hi>Metellus</hi> their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, who being ask'd, What his next Deſign was? Reply'd, <hi>That if he thought his Shirt was privy to any part of his Councel, he would imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately pluck it off and burn it:</hi> And though their <hi>Capitol</hi> was preſerv'd from the <hi>Gauls</hi> by the <hi>Geeſe</hi> that fed therein, yet could they not be perſuaded to carry a <hi>Gooſe</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Corn. Agrig. de Van. Scien.</note> for their Shield, by reaſon they were an Emblem of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Prating:</hi> And he is very well aſſur'd, that the Divulger of a Secret deliver'd by a Friend, (eſpeclally a Potent One) will be imagin'd the ſame as a Treaſonable Diſcovery to a <hi>Prince, Who always loves the Treaſon, but ever
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34357:39"/>hates the Traytor:</hi> And conſequently, will find it attended with as direful Effects; which makes him ever ſhy of receiving any, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently confirms him in the Opinion, that it was well ſaid by<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Plutarch's Morals.</note> 
                  <hi>Philippides</hi> the Comedian, who being ask'd by King <hi>Lyſimachus,</hi> What he deſir'd might be imparted to him? Reply'd, <hi>Any thing but a Secret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as he is far from declaring <hi>Secrets,</hi> ſo he is much further from a <hi>Repetition</hi> of the moſt <hi>common Converſation:</hi> for there is none that has travell'd a days Journey, but knows very well, That a <hi>Gentleman</hi> may expreſs a merry <hi>Reflection,</hi> without meaning any harm; whoſe Repetition would not only create an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Feud, and an immediate ſeparation of the moſt intimate Friendſhip, but has arriv'd to the degree of Murther it ſelf: Such a loqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Perſon merits not the protection of any Civil Government, but a dwelling (pardon the word) among the moſt <hi>Barbarous Infidels,</hi> if they would be ſo unwiſe and unhappy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Him; ſo that herein he wholly remains in the Opinion of <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> who being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to be taught <hi>the Art of Memory,</hi> reply'd, <hi>He much more admir'd the Art of Forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His obliging <hi>Behaviour,</hi> and <hi>charming Mein,</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:34357:39"/>being univerſally diſtributed, he is ſure to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the eſpouſing any particular Party or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; the Inconveniences of which are ſo extravagantly numerous, that they are far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Art of <hi>Rhetorick</hi> to diſcover: For he is aſſur'd upon their Reconciliation, (which cannot be long deferr'd) to find them both unanimouſly join'd to ſurther his prejudice; as the preſum'd Origine of their Separation, and declenſion of that Native Intimacy which otherwiſe (they pretend) might have met with an Eternal Cement, for which Reaſon he ever ſhuns (though frequently provok'd to) that cowardly Vice, Detraction: For beſides that it is the Reverſe of Charity, (the whole deſign of the firſt being to conceal, as well as that of the laſt, to diſcover the Excellencies of any) he can conclude nothing his own that has been once expreſs'd, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaks well (or nothing) of thoſe who no way merit it; and cloiſters up thoſe Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents he conceives may admit of a miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, or diſobliging conſtruction.</p>
               <p>This Conſideration muſt alſo induce him to reſolve, That notwithſtanding his prevailing Circumſtances even neceſſitate him to a large Acquaintance, yet he is poſitive in his paucity of Friends, (and thoſe choſen with the moſt mature and ſedate Deliberation and Judgment he is capable of) ſince they may inſenſibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle him, and irrecoverably twiſt him in their Quarrels. This ſewneſs he obſerves has
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34357:40"/>been highly recommended to him by the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients,</hi> ſince at the moſt they never mention'd them but by<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Plut. Mer. Vol. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pairs:</hi> Thus <hi>Niſus</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Hercules</hi> and <hi>Hylas; Achilles, Patroclus; Pilades, Oreſtes; Titus, Geſippus,</hi> with innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable others: So that though a <hi>Friend</hi> is a <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable Creature,</hi> yet he affects not an <hi>Herd;</hi> and his being uſually call'd and eſteem'd <hi>another Self,</hi> is a convincing Argument that the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>TWO,</hi> is the adequate and compleat mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>Friendſhip:</hi> For as <hi>Briareus,</hi> who with his hundred hands, was daily oblig'd for his bare ſubſiſtance, to feed <hi>Fifty Stomachs,</hi> could thrive no better than our ſelves, who ſupply a ſingle one with <hi>Two;</hi> ſo no one of many <hi>Friends</hi> can boaſt of any other Priviledge, but that of being a Slave to many, and an equal Sharer in all their Diſquietudes.</p>
               <p>I know this <hi>Paucity</hi> has been ſufficiently cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by many, eſpecially in the <hi>Exciſe;</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as they object) abſolutely neceſſary, that an <hi>Officer have many Friends,</hi> if it be only to keep him in, or reinſtate him upon a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge: But if it be conſider'd, that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of this Revenue lies wholly in the hands of thoſe who are poſitive in their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of encouraging Ingenuity, and that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit only ſhall recommend any to their good Opinion; I ſay, if it be conſider'd with what
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34357:40"/>extraordinary Vigor they have turn'd off and expung'd the Ignorant and Diſhoneſt; even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a prevailing Intereſt; no Man that is endow'd with the contrary Qualification, need doubt a Preferment from thoſe who have ever eſteem'd that the only Recommendation.</p>
               <p>However, if upon diſtance of Place a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitor may be thought requiſite, I ſee not why he may not appear under the Notion only of an Acquaintance, and conſequently our Officer is no way neceſſitated to make an addition to his confin'd Number of Friends, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands an Intimacy that is altogether Sacred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:34357:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <p>THE next (though chiefeſt) Particular our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> reſolves on, is, that he runs not in Debt; he is ſatisfied that thoſe extravagant Expreſſions of Friendſhip he finds in his preſent place of Reſidence, meets with a correſpondent duration, and continues no longer than himſelf, a remove of 20 Miles making it to vaniſh, as if they had been ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than ſtrangers, and utterly unknown be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for he that but a day ſince ſaluted him with—<hi>SIR, YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R MOST, H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MBLE SERVANT, I ſhould be extremely Ambitious of ſeeing you at my Houſe, where you will find a Glaſs of as good, though I ſay it, as any in Town, wholly devoted for your Service; Why don't you come to my Shop? I proteſt I'le uſe you very kindly, I will not deſire to get a Farthing by you, Try me for once: I have often admir'd at your great ſtrangeneſs, your Predeceſſor and I were extremely intimate, and I ſerv'd him with the beſt Cloth, Stuff,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Country could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, though there is a ſmall Reckoning, between us ſtill, an inconſiderable Drib remaining; yet if I never ſee him again, 'tis not the firſt Loſs I have had—But pray where is he—I am ſure he came to Town clad in window'd Rags, which demonſtrated him to ſpring from an Illuſtrious
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34357:41"/>Houſe, the Sun ſbining through him. Nay, he was ſo bare, that a Lowſe might have broke her Neck from the beſt Suit in his poſſeſſion; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I truſted him in meer Civility, when no Body would: And my Kindneſſes were ſo exceſſive, that I vow I got not a Penny by him, I letting him have my Goods as they coſt me out of my own Pocket. His Wife too had many things unknown to him, and was ſo ungenteel as to go away, and never take her leave: But that ſmall Sum my Wife lent her in ready Money, vexes me really more than all the rest: For God's ſake, Sir, when did you hear from them? Can you put me in a way? I declare the best Gloves in Town are ſo very much at your Service, that I will ſend for them immediately.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, He that but juſt now admir'd ev'n the ſhadow of your Shoe-ſtrings; nay, that could never be himſelf, or enjoy the leaſt Satisfaction upon your Abſence, and ſo much doated on your Perſon and Parts, that he was ever ſure to ſecure you at leaſt for a Sundays Dinner, he certainly finds now to accoſt him with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Raſcal, a Pitiful Beggarly Fellow.</hi> And, <hi>in fine,</hi> reiterates with all his Elocution, the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical Flouriſhes he was graciouſly pleas'd to beſtow upon his Predeceſſor. All this being the Reſult of one of his Three Fundamental Points, which he ever eſteems as Sacred. The firſt is, becauſe he ſuppoſes it an Impoſſibility now to get any more from him. The ſecond is, becauſe they think it their Duty to load the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34357:42"/>abſent <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> with all the ſcurrilous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections their quaint Parts are capable of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing: Or (which is certainly his ſecureſt Reaſon) becauſe he took not up his conſtant Diſcharge upon every individual Payment, without which, our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> concludes it a <hi>Doomſday-Book,</hi> and himſelf therefore in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal danger: For this he is certainly aſſur'd of, that his croſſing the Book is no diſcharge of the Debt, ſome keeping two Books, and one of them fairly Seven Years after he has ſeen put in execution, upon his having no Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or upon the bare preſumption of its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loſt: But this being detected by its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, it would make a <hi>Stoick</hi> burſt to hear his Excuſe—
<q>I Vow, Wife, this Idle Boy, this Raſcal of an Apprentice of ours, has certainly abus'd this Honest Gentleman; I am ſure I remember ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, he or you, my Dear, have forgot to croſs the Book, and conſequently have neceſſitated me to commit an Incivility, which I was never known (as all my honest Neighbours can atteſt) to perpetrate before.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Reſult of the whole is, That our <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe-Man</hi> is even afrighted from being Laviſh in his Expences, and therefore is ſure to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe a ſuitable moderation in them; for he knows very well, That although the Goddeſs <hi>Diana</hi> gave heretofore, in the City of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to ſuch Debtors as could fly into her Temple,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34357:42"/>Freedom and Protection againſt their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, yet he knows too that Her Power ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving met with a Ceſſation, there remains not an <hi>Aſylum</hi> for him, but a <hi>Ludgate</hi> or a <hi>Compter.</hi> He has that poſitive regard to the worth of a Penny, that nothing but Neceſſity ſhall extort it. The Miſery, nay the Pleuriſy of Griefs, as well as the Scandal that always attend its Want, are infallible Arguments for him to be more than parſimonious. A prudent Frugali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is recommended to all, but to him even Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs it ſelf cannot be accounted any Crime, ſince he has a Regiment of convincing Motives to it that do not any way concern the reſt of Mankind. And as 'tis obſerv'd that there are particular Cates ordain'd by Nature as peculiar to the Temperaments and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the particular Inhabitants of that Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate under which they are fix'd, ſo he ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorily embraces an Earthen Cup, as moſt agreeable to his Mold, and never aims at thoſe (to him) inſipid, becauſe gilded Fopperies, which terminate in a Gaol:
<q>
                     <l>For if his Drink but a cold Moiſture have,</l>
                     <l>No other charming Qualities doth crave;</l>
                     <l>And with a rich Contentment can reſign</l>
                     <l>To others all the Pleaſures of the Vine.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But knowing that the enlarging on this To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick, would interfere with what has been, as well as what is to be ſaid, I ſhall here reduce
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34357:43"/>the whole, and conclude with Two Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p>As a Man, he knows what Nature, by the ſmalneſs of his Mouth and Throat, has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with him, that he ſhould eat but little, and has therefore given a correſpondent place of Reception; and, as an Officer, he is advis'd by Providence to devour leſs, conſidering the Scantneſs of his Fortunes, and (which is more) the frequent Viciſſitudes that inevitably attend them, an Ordinary therefore of 8 <hi>d.</hi> is eſteem'd by him Extraordinary, and he ever departs with the ſame Satisfaction, as if with <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> he had impoveriſh'd the Seas, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled the Air, and wholly extirpated the very <hi>Species</hi> of all Terreſtrial Animals, to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify a ſenſual and inſatiate Palate, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very much prefers a Dinner with <hi>Camil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> or the <hi>Curii,</hi> before that of a Beſtial and Intemperate <hi>Sardanapalus</hi>—He knows it would be Ridiculous in him to be Nice, whoſe Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence expects a daily Revolution of <hi>in Stain quo:</hi> And he is ſure to perform himſelf what he finds commanded in <hi>Suetonius</hi> by <hi>Julius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> who, to repreſs extravagant Diet, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet a Guard upon all Butchers Shops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but ſent his Officers to particular Houſes; to take away (though at their Tables) ſuch Diſhes as either eſcap'd them, or were eſteem'd ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous; and that even from thoſe who were qualified for the greateſt Affairs of State, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34357:43"/>this he concludes obligatory from him who has nothing certain but uncertainty. In ſhort, his Table is not furniſh'd much unlike to what the Poet deſcribes of <hi>Oberon</hi>'s:
<q>
                     <l>A little Muſhrome Table ſpread,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Viand's but of Barley Bread;</l>
                     <l>Or Yellow Corn of Parkie Wheat,</l>
                     <l>With ſome ſmall Sandy Gritts to eat.</l>
                     <l>His choice Bits with and in a Trice,</l>
                     <l>He makes a Feaſt leſs Great than Nice;</l>
                     <l>And willingly takes what is ſent,</l>
                     <l>He crowns the Grace-Cup with Content.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond Exceſs our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence commands him to avoid, is that of <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel.</hi> And here I ſhall not play the <hi>Divine,</hi> by offering thoſe convincing Arguments and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Motives, which engage all Mankind to a ſtrict obſervance, it being much above my Province: But ſhall only inſinuate ſome few Notions which peculiarly relate to him, to keep within his proper Bounds and Limits, and which even neceſſitate him to a Compliance, by all the Obligations imaginable. Our <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe-Man</hi> remembers it is no ſmall Addition to the great Character of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> when it is recorded, That he never wore any thing about him but what was Home-made, and of the ſpinning of his own Family; and he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think it a Diminution of his Credit, that his Attire ſuits with his Circumſtances, which
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34357:44"/>are plain and ſimple. He knows how ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous he muſt prove, if, with the Bird of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, his Feathers ſhould be much more valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able than the Carcaſs; or with the Cinamon-Tree, that the Bark only is eſteem'd, and the Tree it ſelf of little or no uſe. A tolerable Gayety in others, would be altogether intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in him; and his only Ambition is to front a Winter, and arrive to the Character of Decent. He knows that Credit is compar'd to the Chaſtity of a M—which, if once broke, is ever after loſt; and, if not kept up, is like a Palace, which for want of Repair falls to Ruin. And as it is his chief deſign to ſecure it, ſo he knows there is no way for the exact performance of it, but to cut his Coat according to his Cloth, by which he knows he ſhall be diſengag'd from Dependance, and lying at the Mercy of the Mercileſs; for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence has given us Frize, and courſer Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when our neceſſitous Circumſtances can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or may not aſpire to Sattins, and all to continue us in our priſtine Liberty and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: For beſides the Scandal and Univerſal Cenſures that muſt attend the dreſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond one's Quality, the dread of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible in a Gaol ſufficiently deters him; <hi>A place which is the Grave of the Living, the Houſe of meager Looks, and deſtructive Smells; a place that teacheth Wiſdom much too late; the Dunghil of the Law, where the Ruines of the Gentry, and heaps of decay'd Bankrupts inſeparably meet. In
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34357:44"/>fine, 'tis the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Anonimus.</note> 
                  <hi>poor Scholars, where only Three Things are ſtudied, to Pray, Curſe, and Write Letters.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T ſtay—<hi>Apollo</hi> with your <hi>Sacred Nine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If Pow'r ye have deſcend,</l>
                     <l>And your Aſſiſtance lend;</l>
                     <l>If as ye boaſt ye are Divine,</l>
                     <l>Inſpire with an <hi>uncommon Line</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncommon! Nay, your chiefeſt Excellence,</l>
                     <l>Your chiefeſt Eloquence)</l>
                     <l>That it might with the <hi>Subject</hi> equally tranſcend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>HE that ne're <hi>Pegaſus</hi> beſtrid</l>
                     <l>May ſhew his untaught Skill;</l>
                     <l>And he that never did</l>
                     <l>Aſcend the Sacred and <hi>admir'd Hill,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>May ſometimes <hi>ſtumbling</hi> wittily rehearſe</l>
                     <l>The Excellencies of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe;</l>
                     <l>For he that <hi>trots in Proſe,</hi> may ſurely <hi>walk in Verſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:34357:45"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>HEnce then ye ſweating Pleaſures of the Plow</l>
                     <l>That only Labour know,</l>
                     <l>Who <hi>Cheveron</hi> their Mother Earth,</l>
                     <l>And by their Furrows cannot grieve,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Nero,</hi> they behold their place of Birth,</l>
                     <l>And thus exclude</l>
                     <l>Filial Gratitude,</l>
                     <l>As never to believe</l>
                     <l>That ſhe must them again receive.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <l>ADieu ye Toyling Sons of Trade,</l>
                     <l>That only the Curs'd Plague of Bus'neſs find,</l>
                     <l>No Cultivating of the Mind,</l>
                     <l>When all the Arts they want</l>
                     <l>Which yet we cannot grant,</l>
                     <l>Are Impoſitions on the Ignorant,</l>
                     <l>Theſe Statute-Slaves are made.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <l>HEnce ye Alarms of the <hi>Vermilion God,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Farewel the Crimſon Shield,</l>
                     <l>And the loud Actions of the Field,</l>
                     <l>That lay the greedy Dust with drops of Blood,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Excellence abounds</l>
                     <l>In dreadful Sounds,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Summum Bonum</hi> is in Wounds.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:34357:45"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <l>WHile with inventive Brain</l>
                     <l>We must advance to an Harmonious Strain,</l>
                     <l>And ſince the Subject doth inſpire,</l>
                     <l>We only the <hi>EXCISE</hi> admire,</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Bus'neſs, Pleaſure, Wit</hi> agree,</l>
                     <l>As if the <hi>Three</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Here met with their admir'd Monopoly.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:34357:46"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <p>THus have I hinted to you ſome <hi>few Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks</hi> in relation to our <hi>Exciſe-Man's Qualifications in the ARTS and MEN,</hi> I ſhould now demonſtrate his <hi>Excellency in the knowledge of the LAWS;</hi> without which, he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fied he is like thoſe who are eternally m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed up in Blindneſs, and are wholly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant how to direct their motion, ſince they know not when they err. He knows this to be the certain and infallible Guide, and to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant herein, implies an Ignorance in all. The <hi>Law</hi> is like a <hi>ſecond Sun,</hi> which enlightens his Road, and hereby wholly creates a Progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is both ſafe and pleaſant: This, is it that procures an undaunted Boldneſs in the proſecution of his Buſineſs; and this is it that ſecures him from the treacherous deſigns of the moſt malevolent; ſo that he is ever found an <hi>Intellectus Agens,</hi> till he has plan'd thoſe knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Points which ſeem'd to be his only Rubs, and reſts n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with the leaſt ſatisfaction, 'til he has made that <hi>Conquest</hi> which ſhould not admit of another <hi>Rally:</hi> But for the preretited Reaſons ſhall at preſent wave Particulars, and deſcend to demonſtrate ſome few of thoſe <hi>Excellencies,</hi> as well as <hi>Pleaſures</hi> and <hi>Advantages,</hi> that inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34357:46"/>attend the Employment of our <hi>Exciſe-Man,</hi> and conſequently ſhall bring him from his <hi>Study,</hi> and trace him <hi>abroad</hi> in all his <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing Felicities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>first-Advantage</hi> then, which I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on, that follows our <hi>Exciſe-Man's Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> is, That it is not to be purchas'd with <hi>Money:</hi> They have a Competency (at leaſt) without paying for't, a conſiderable Income for nothing expended, and a Fortune very much above that which can be term'd <hi>Mean,</hi> for ſeeking it. It has been ever held, That nothing can be done without that glittering as well as bewitching Oar, <hi>Gold,</hi> which is ſaid to be that <hi>General Charm,</hi> which nothing can <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt;</hi> that abſolute <hi>Neceſſarium,</hi> that nothing can be begun or perfected without it. In ſhort, It is allow'd that there cannot be any living, without that <hi>Saint-ſeducing Metal,</hi> which we here find perfectly contradictory; Our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> having a <hi>Compleat Maintenance</hi> without <hi>Charge;</hi> a <hi>Sufficiency</hi> without <hi>Dependance;</hi> and a pleaſant <hi>Subſiſtence</hi> without a <hi>Bribe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſecondly, It is confeſs'd that <hi>Poverty</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects the moſt Ambitious Thoughts, and he that before could with <hi>Ovid</hi>'s <hi>Gyants</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> , have ſtorm'd even <hi>Heaven</hi> it ſelf, appears now the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34357:47"/>moſt contemptible on <hi>Earth.</hi> He that could charm the World with the moſt Rhetorical Flouriſhes imaginable, and, with <hi>Amphion,</hi> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate and intrance the Dulleſt of Souls, is now become mute. And he that juſt now bluſh'd at the thoughts of an <hi>Ill Action,</hi> fears not<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> now its Perpetration, with all its dreadful <hi>Concomitants.</hi> On the contrary, it is acknowledg'd, That <hi>Abundance</hi> and <hi>Contentment</hi> are very rarely <hi>yok'd,</hi> but <hi>Care</hi> is ever their inſeparable Page; for whoever is poſſeſs'd with it, is either perplex'd with the Avarice of acquiring more, or the extravagant trouble of ſecuring that already in their poſſeſſion, ſo that we find a <hi>Mean</hi> the moſt eſtimable; for <hi>Extreams</hi> have violent <hi>Ends,</hi> and in their greateſt <hi>Glory</hi> are deſtroy'd, ſince like Fire and Powder, they are no ſooner met but are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd: And as the moſt ſtately <hi>Hills</hi> produce but little, and are parch'd by the too near vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinity of <hi>Phabus</hi>'s ſcorching Rays, ſo muſt we own, that thoſe Valleys are but <hi>barren,</hi> whoſe diſtance from his reviving <hi>heat</hi> we find to be extraordinary; ſo that they are as <hi>ſick</hi> that <hi>ſurfeit</hi> with <hi>too much,</hi> as they that <hi>ſtarve</hi> with <hi>nothing;</hi> and conſequently we may conclude, That as the Eaſt and Weſt upon the Globe are divided only by a Mathematical Point, ſo Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and Miſery with all Extremes are ſtill contiguous, a <hi>Mean</hi> was ever held the ſafeſt:
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34357:47"/>And he was no Fool, that wiſh'd his Fate had confin'd him between an High-Conſtable, and a Juſtice of Peace, that he might enjoy a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Mediocrity; for the <hi>Rich</hi> are expos'd to the <hi>Envy,</hi> and the <hi>Poor</hi> to the <hi>Contempt</hi> of all. This is our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi>'s Felicity, who having neither <hi>Poverty</hi> or <hi>Riches,</hi> cannot be dejected by the <hi>former,</hi> nor puffed up with the <hi>latter.</hi> This is our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> happineſs, who being poſſeſs'd of a true <hi>Mean,</hi> is above the Plague that Penury attends, and below the gilded Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of Grandure, who having the deſir'd Competency, is not <hi>troubled</hi> with the <hi>Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the <hi>first,</hi> nor <hi>afflicted</hi> with the <hi>Troubles</hi> of the <hi>last.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This then being that ſtate of Life which has been ever coveted by all the <hi>thinking</hi> part of <hi>Mankind,</hi> we cannot deny but our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> fully enjoys: And though his Fifty is not Five hundred, yet he is ſatisfied the difference is but a <hi>Cypher,</hi> which he reckons of <hi>no value,</hi> eſpecially ſince it exhibits not (that which every one ſeems deſirous of) <hi>Contentment,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Conſideration he hath a great regard to and value for his Employment, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently doth wholly acquieſce in the Opinion of <hi>Horace,</hi> Lib. 2. Ode 10.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:34357:48"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Wiſe they, that with a cautious Fear</l>
                  <l>Not always thro the Ocean ſteer;</l>
                  <l>Nor, whilst they think the Winds will roar,</l>
                  <l>Do thrust too near the Rocky Shoar:</l>
                  <l>To thoſe that chuſe the <hi>Golden Mean,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Waves are ſmooth, the Skies ſerene.</l>
                  <l>They want the Baſeneſs of the Poors retreat,</l>
                  <l>And alſo th' envy'd Houſes of the Great.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:34357:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>I Proceed to the <hi>Third Advantage</hi> that attends him, which is <hi>Travel;</hi> the Excellency of which, and the great <hi>Encomiums</hi> on it, may be ſufficiently ſeen in almoſt innumerable other <hi>Books:</hi> For there is ſcarce any of our <hi>Voyagers,</hi> or <hi>Foreign Itinerants,</hi> that have exhibited any thing of <hi>Memorables</hi> to the <hi>Publick,</hi> but have largely dilated on it, and ſome of them with that bewitching Language, and captivating Arguments, that they have directly charm'd many <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> who finding its Reality con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by Ocular Demonſtration, have aſſerted again the like to others, who are thereby wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly engag'd to the ſame Performances, and ſo <hi>ad infinitum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not expatiate upon every particular Advantage that immediately attends it, as the procuring and continuing <hi>Health, Reading of Men,</hi> and the remarkable Obſervables they continually meet; Nor the ſeveral <hi>Pleaſures</hi> that infallibly attend them, they having no relation here, and beſides too troubleſom in the Tranſcription: But ſhall only obſerve, they generally have made that of Foreign the greateſt, if not the whole Subject of their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyricks,</hi> which has been ever with me the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34357:49"/>great Product of Admiration, to ſee a <hi>Spark,</hi> after many years Travel, to the extravagant Expence both of <hi>Money and Time,</hi> to have learnt nothing but to <hi>Swear handſomly, Wh— genteely,</hi> and <hi>Drink compleatly;</hi> and, if they had ever any thing, forgot that, and return much worſe than they went, for want of a prudent management of their <hi>Time,</hi> and improvement of it by a ſufficient <hi>Bottom,</hi> before their admir'd Voyage:
<q>
                     <l>For Travelling creates no Senſe we know,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dunces</hi> come <hi>back</hi> as genuine as they <hi>go.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And ask them a particular Deſcription of any Rarity they met with, their whole Diſcourſe tends to no more than what is thus expreſs'd by another <hi>Poet,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>There was a Mouſe went up a Wall,</l>
                     <l>When ſhe fell down ſhe had a Fall.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Not that I would pretend to a <hi>Diminution</hi> of the <hi>Excellency</hi> of <hi>Foreign Travel,</hi> but allow it an extraordinary Form in the qualification of a <hi>Compleat Gentleman,</hi> not abſtracting <hi>Domeſtick;</hi> which ought to have the <hi>firſt</hi> ſhare, at leaſt, in it, and to be the very <hi>Prologue</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> to all his future Accompliſhments: For let any pretend to what Education they pleaſe, in my opinion he will ſhew himſelf but <hi>ignorantly bred,</hi> that ſhall only be capable of <hi>giving</hi> an account (which very few can that) of <hi>another,</hi> and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34357:49"/>know <hi>nothing</hi> of his <hi>own Country:</hi> For although the unknowing part of the World may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that there are no extraordinary Curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties but what may be ſeen abroad, yet if they pleaſe to ſuſpend their preſent thoughts, and alleviate ſomewhat of their innate Prejudice and Partiality, and take a narrow Scrutiny and Trial, they will find it inferior to <hi>none:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Inſula praedives, quae toto vix eget orbe,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A wealthy Iſland which no help deſires,</l>
                        <l>Yet all the World Supply from her requires;</l>
                        <l>Able to glut King <hi>Solomon</hi> with Pleaſures,</l>
                        <l>And furſeit great <hi>Anguſtus</hi> with her Treaſures.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And again:
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Anglia, Mons, Pons, Fons, Eccleſia, Foemina, Lana.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>England</hi> is ſtor'd with Mountains, Bridges, Wooll,</l>
                        <l>With Churches, Rivers, Women Beautiful.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Or, to expreſs it by a more modern Proſe Author, ſhe is the Churches firſt Daughter, having the firſt Chriſtian King, and out of whoſe Bowels ſprung the firſt Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, that little World, ſo ſelf-ſufficient,<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that ſhe ſeems to thruſt away from her all the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34357:50"/>World beſides, as being a perfect <hi>Subſtantive,</hi> that can ſtand by her ſelf. Beſides, it may be poſitively affirm'd, That there is not any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Advantage that accrues abroad, or any Obſervable, but may be equaliz'd, if not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell'd, at home; for is he covetous of the Company of Learned Men, no Foreign Place can pretend to a Competition? Is he deſirous to ſee the Miracles of Nature, it cannot be excell'd by any; Or is he ambitious of view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Noble Structures, Fields, Gardens, Fruits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he cannot ſind them ſo abſolutely reign in their excellency any where, ſo great as in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nature her ſelf does here in Triumph ride,</l>
                  <l>And makes this Place the ground of all her Pride,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe various Flowers cheat the raſher Eye,</l>
                  <l>In taking them for curious Tapeſtry.</l>
                  <l>A ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver Spring down from a Rock does fall,</l>
                  <l>That in a Draught would ſerve to water all</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the edges of a graſſy Bank,</l>
                  <l>A Tuft of Trees grow circling in a Rank;</l>
                  <l>So fair, ſo freſh, ſo ſweet, ſo green a Ground,</l>
                  <l>The piercing Eye of Heav'n yet never found.</l>
                  <l>So ſweet the Air, ſo moderate the Clime,</l>
                  <l>None ſickly lives or dies before his Time.</l>
                  <l>Heaven ſure has kept this ſpot of Earth uncurs't,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew how all things were created firſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>O fortunata &amp; omnibus Terris beatior Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia! Te omnibus Coeli ac ſoli ditavit Natura, Tibi nihil ineſt quod vitae offendat, Tibi nihil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34357:50"/>quod vita deſideret, ita ut alter Orbis extra Orbem poni ad delicias humani generis videaris.</hi> Oh happy and bleſſed <hi>Britain!</hi> above all other Countries in the World, Nature hath enrich'd thee with all the Bleſſings of Heaven and Earth; nothing in thee is hurtful to Mankind, nothing wanting in thee that is deſirable: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch that thou ſeemeſt another World pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beſides, or without the great one, meerly for the delight and pleaſure of Mankind. Thus alſo the Poet:
<q>
                     <l>Quicquid amat luxus, quicquid deſiderat uſus,</l>
                     <l>Ex Te proveniunt vel aliunde Tibi.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus having given ſome <hi>ſmall</hi> Hints of the <hi>great</hi> Advantages that attend the knowing of our own Countrey, I ſhall as briefly acquaint you who is the only competent Judge of it, and that excels any in this extraordinary Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; for there is no Rarity, as Scituation, Diviſion, Honourable Titles, Hiſtorical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks, or Character of any County in general, or Town in particular, but our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> perfectly enjoys, and can give an immediate ſatisfaction and account of; and that this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deni'd, ſhall be proved by the following Inſtance, among many others, that might have been as properly incerted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:34357:51"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI. Glouceſterſhire</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>DIVISION.</head>
                  <p>IT is divided into Thirty Hundreds, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Twenty ſix Marke-Towns, Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and eight Pariſh-Churches, and in the Dioceſs of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>PARLIAMENT-MEN.</head>
                  <p>It elects Eight Members; for the County Two; for the City of <hi>Glouceſttr</hi> Two; <hi>Tewks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> Two; <hi>Cirenceſter</hi> Two.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE TITLES.</head>
                  <p>This City gave the Title to a Duke, the youngeſt Son of King <hi>Charles I.</hi> but he expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the Year 1662. it now gives that Title to the eldeſt Son of <hi>George</hi> Prince of <hi>Denmark;</hi> and <hi>Berkley</hi> Caſtle, gives the Title of Earl to <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Berkley.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:34357:51"/>
                  <head>SCIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ATION.</head>
                  <p>This County hath <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Warwick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhires</hi> on the North, <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> on the Eaſt, <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> on the <hi>South, Hereford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhre</hi> with the River <hi>Wye</hi> on the Weſt, the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Seaverne</hi> running through it.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Natural and Artificial Rarities.</head>
                     <p n="1">(1.) There is not any exceeds the River <hi>Seaterne</hi> for Breadth of Channel, Swiftneſs of Stream, or Multiplicity of Fiſh. There is in it (ſays <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bury</hi>) a daily Rage and Fury of the Waters, raiſing up the Sands, winding and driving them into Heaps, and ſometimes overflowing its Banks, covering the bordering Grounds, though immediately retiring. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy is the Veſſel it taketh full upon the ſide, but the Watermen hearing it, they prepare themſelves to meet it, by which they cut the Waves, and avoid the danger. This encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Salt and Freſh Water is call'd the <hi>Higre</hi> or Eager, for the keenneſs and fie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>eneſs thereof, which is occaſion'd (ſaith <hi>Bruannia Baconica</hi>) by the ſeveral Tides, which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately meeting, force it up with that Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that it very uſually ſwims (as I may call it) over the Water Six Foot, which comes in at <hi>Glouceſter</hi> all at once, of which hear an old Poet:
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34357:52"/>
                        <q>
                           <l>— <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil they be embraced</l>
                           <l>In <hi>Seavern</hi>'s Sovereign Arms, with thoſe tumultuous Waves</l>
                           <l>Shut up in narrower Bounds the <hi>Higre</hi> wildly raves,</l>
                           <l>And frights the ſtragling Flocks, the neighbouring Shoars to fly</l>
                           <l>Afar as from the Main it comes with hideous cry.</l>
                           <l>And on the angry Front the curled Foam doth bring</l>
                           <l>The Billows 'gainſt the Banks which fiercely it doth fling.</l>
                           <l>Throws up the ſiimy Oar, and makes the ſcaly Brood</l>
                           <l>Leap madding to the Land, affrighted from the Flood.</l>
                           <l>Or'eturns the toiling Barge whoſe Steerſman doth not launch,</l>
                           <l>And thruſts the ſurrowing Beak into her dreadful Paunch.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">(2.) The Cathedral Church of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> is a beautiful Building, and conſiſt; of a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Window-work, wherein is the famous Whiſpering-place, thus deſcribed: If you ſpeak here againſt a Wall ſoftly, another ſhall hear you voice (30 or 40 Feet) better than he that's near you: I ſuppoſe (ſays Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi>) there is ſome Vault, or Hollow, or Iſle behind the Wall, and ſome paſſage to it, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the further end of that Wall, againſt which you ſpeak; ſo as the voice of him that ſpeaketh, ſlideth along the Wall, and then entreth at ſome paſſage, and communicateth with the Air of the hollow, for it is ſomewhat
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34357:52"/>preſerv'd by the plain Wall, but that is too weak to give an Audible Sound, till it hath communicated with the Back Air.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>HISTORICAL REMARKS.</head>
                  <p>In this Church lies <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> eldeſt Son to <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> in a painted wooden Tomb, in the midſt of the Quire, whoſe Eyes were burnt out in <hi>Cardiffo</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Glamorganſhire</hi> (where he was kept Priſoner 26 years) by Braſs Baſons. And here alſo the unhappy Ring <hi>Edward</hi> II. lies buried, under a Monument of Alablaſter, who, in the 20th year of his Reign, was depos'd by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>This County (ſaith Dr. <hi>Fuller</hi>) did breed a Plaintiff and Defendant<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Worthies, pag. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> , which betwixt them (with many Altercations) traverſed the longeſt Suit I ever read of in <hi>England;</hi> for a Su t was commenc'd between the Heirs of Sir <hi>Thomas Talbot,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Liſle,</hi> againſt the Heirs of the Lord <hi>Berkley,</hi> about certain Lands in the County; the Suit began in the end of the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. and was depending until King <hi>Jame</hi> the Firſt's time, when it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded after the expiration of One hundred and forty Years.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:34357:53"/>
                  <p>He finds that in the 17th Year of Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi>'s Reign, the 24th of <hi>February,</hi> at <hi>Tewks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> in this County, a miraculous thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd after a Flood: In an Afternoon there came down the River <hi>Avon</hi> a great number of Flies and Beetles, ſuch as in the Summer Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings uſe to ſtrike Men on the face, a Foot thick on the Water, ſo that in credible Mens Judgments, there were within a pair of Butts length, about One hundred Quarters of thoſe Flies; the Milis were quite damm'd up with them for the ſpace of four days; they were cleans'd, by digging them out with Shovels: from whence they came is yet unknown, but the day was cold, and an hard Froſt.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are ſome few of the many Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vables our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> makes in his pleaſing Travels, and were it not for enlarging theſe Papers beyond their intended Limits, I could from him exhibit the particular Deſcription, Government, Cuſtoms, Natural, as well as Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Rarities, of every particular Village; and therefore ſhall only add, that of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence he muſt be the moſt competent Judge of making a <hi>Geographical Deſcription</hi> of every Road, that inſtead of Miles, can tell you the very Steps; and the moſt exact <hi>Hiſtoriographer</hi> when nothing worthy of <hi>Remark</hi> can miſs his <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>He is — but Time denies to tell thee what,</l>
                     <l>Sum all Perfections up, and he is that.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:34357:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <p>HAving ſomewhat largely inſiſted on the <hi>Excellency of our Exciſe-Man</hi> in relation to Domeſtick Travel, and his exact Knowledge of every particular Place in his own Country, it may not be amiſs to ſubjoin a few Lines of that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile dulci,</hi> thoſe <hi>Pleaſures as well as Profits</hi> (which are ſuppos'd to be the Epitome of all humane Wiſhes) that indubitably attend him as a natural <hi>Conſequent</hi> of the <hi>Premiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No ſooner is our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> poſſeſs'd with all things that can properly make him ſo, and <hi>Aurora</hi>'s ruddy Cheeks produce the Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth of a day, but he anticipates <hi>Sols</hi> more reſplendent Rays, by ſuing out a Writ of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce againſt the bewitching Charms of Death-reſembling <hi>Morpheus,</hi> and is immediately ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs'd with all the Pleaſures of a Countrey Life—
<q>
                     <l>No War diſturbs his reſt with fierce Alarms,</l>
                     <l>No angry Seas offend,</l>
                     <l>He ſhuns the Law, and thoſe ambitious Charms</l>
                     <l>Which great Men do attend. —</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Life with which the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, and has been ever held in an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34357:54"/>Veneration; and has alſo been particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly obſerv'd to be more natural and familiar with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> than with any other whatſoever: And were it poſſible to give it is prower Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, we ought to look on <hi>Calen</hi> and <hi>Hypoora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> impertinent, and their <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> wholly unneceſſary; <hi>Schola Salerni</hi> might have burn'd their gingling Diſticks, ſince here we find them altogether <hi>uſeleſs:</hi> And if by chance a Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptom ſhould appear, every Tree, Field or Hedge produces a <hi>Panpharmacon,</hi> that <hi>Remedium in omnes Morbos,</hi> which the more <hi>Simple Druggiſts</hi> never can. Nay, 'tis Demonſtration, that it is ſo in the opinion of the general part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, in regard that let their Avocations be ever ſo urgent, their Circumſtances ever ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, yet they will cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> attempt a ſhort enjoyment of it, as their proper <hi>Aſylum</hi> for renewing that health (which almoſt was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd unto a deſperation) by a much more lively Air.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juſtice here left her last Impreſſion when</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She fled from the defil'd Abodes of Men.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>Ovid Metam.</bibl>
               <p>And as this Life extremely contributes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that ineſtimable Gem, Health; ſo its excellency would further appear, if we had leiſure to enlarge upon the ſeveral <hi>Topicks,</hi> as their living in thoſe unenvied Shades, and the only retirement from the crowd and noiſe of thronged Towns and Cities, (where nothing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34357:54"/>elſe is found but that which muſt be call'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd) but I cannot omit the ſaying ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Pleaſures our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> daily meets with, in the fruition of ſuch an <hi>happy Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis here (and only here) he meets thoſe verdant ſhades that ſuffer (if not force) him to think of himſelf, where he not only miſſes every thing that can pretend to create an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion of Thought without his Licence, but even finds incomparable Inducements and Aſſiſtants towards its performance: The ſight of thoſe pleaſing Walks, the regularity of thoſe ambitious Trees that ſcreen us from the Sun's moſt violent and ſcorching ſtays, and (with <hi>Ovid</hi>'s Giants) not only poſſeſs the Earth, but make a hold Attempt at Heaven.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Theſe charming Woods exiling <hi>Phoebus</hi> Rays,</l>
                  <l>Where no rude Eawn, or wanton Sylvan plays;</l>
                  <l>No Beaſt makes here his Den, no Wind can blow</l>
                  <l>With all its force to hurt an hallow'd Bough.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Together with the hearing the bewitching, though natural <hi>Harmony</hi> of thoſe <hi>flying Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſters</hi> of the Wood; I ſay, he that his Stars has (with our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi>) been ſo propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to, as to enjoy theſe Felicities of our Earthly Paradiſe, and cannot glut his <hi>Five Senſes,</hi> can never be allow'd <hi>One,</hi> but a place in the loweſt Form with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthinking Mob;</hi> but
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34357:55"/>our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> even hugs himſelf into an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of thoſe Qualifications he had ſo happily before.</p>
               <p>But as the too long enjoyment of the moſt charming Varieties palls our Appetite, which will quickly create our mean Opinion of them without a ſmall Divorce; ſo our <hi>Officer,</hi> if he had the greateſt inclinations to a longer poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them to occaſion this Surfeit, yet his <hi>Buſineſs</hi> even <hi>neceſſitates</hi> him to a more uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined fruition of larger Varieties.</p>
               <p>He cannot advance himſelf, but he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly met with that general <hi>Gaol Delivery</hi> of all the vigorous Seeds and Flowers, lately in cuſtody of the pinching Froſt; the ſight of whoſe bewitching hue, infallibly creates a <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhment,</hi> a much too mean a word for ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments; theſe are alſo attended with em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broider'd Fields and Meadows, pav'd with the beauteous Violet and Primroſe, wherein he quickly views poor <hi>Strephon</hi> deſcant on the great Perfections of his too cruel <hi>Phillis.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <head>(I.)</head>
                     <l>TELL me ye Heathen Deities above,</l>
                     <l>Can there be greater than the God of Love?</l>
                     <l>And oh! <hi>Commanding Cupid</hi> ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>Is there any that you prize,</l>
                     <l>Like that in <hi>Celia</hi>'s Eyes?</l>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:34357:55"/>
                     <l>Within whoſe <hi>Boſom</hi> lies the <hi>Milky Way,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in whoſe Smiles the Sunſhine of the Day.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>(2.)</head>
                     <l>Most Glorious <hi>Stamp</hi> of Humane Race,</l>
                     <l>We yet can ſee</l>
                     <l>Not one of them ſo Great as Thee;</l>
                     <l>All Hail then mighty <hi>Princeſs:</hi> Now</l>
                     <l>At the Altars of your Eyes,</l>
                     <l>I bleed a Sacrifice,</l>
                     <l>And were the <hi>Indies</hi> mine, I would ſubmit</l>
                     <l>Quickly to lay its Treaſures at your Feet.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>(3.)</head>
                     <l>See how the Ruby Roſes,</l>
                     <l>See how they upon your Cheek</l>
                     <l>A freſh Ingrafture ſeek;</l>
                     <l>See, ſee, how Gay they, <hi>Celia,</hi> look,</l>
                     <l>And all things Serene appear,</l>
                     <l>Only becauſe you're here,</l>
                     <l>And though bright <hi>Sol</hi> be preſent, I must ſay</l>
                     <l>You are the Light and Splendor of the Day.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>'Tis here only he may perceive Bounteous <hi>Ceres</hi> in all her State and Glory, and <hi>Sail</hi> with Pleaſure in a prodigious <hi>Sea of Corn,</hi> without the hazard of <hi>drowning,</hi> till its <hi>quality</hi> meets with a <hi>total Alteration.</hi> Here only we enjoy that <hi>Beatus Ille</hi> which <hi>Horace</hi> ſo much doted on, and all admire but thoſe that never had it: Thoſe chryſtal Fountains, ſtately Hills,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34357:56"/>embroider'd Vales, and thoſe muttering as well as ſtrugling Rivulets, are certainly able to create a Total Eclipſe upon the Dulleſt of Souls, and to entrance the meaneſt of Faculties into an unaccuſtom'd Admiration:
<q>
                     <l>Whoſe Streams on purling Pebbles Murinure keep,</l>
                     <l>Which may invite and ſummon Gentle Sleep;</l>
                     <l>Where Waves call Waves, and glide along in Ranks,</l>
                     <l>And prattle to the Water-edging Banks,</l>
                     <l>And gives a Gentle Kiſs to every Sedge</l>
                     <l>She overtaketh in her Pilgrimage.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe the <hi>Buſtling Town</hi> would fain pretend to alſo by their Gardens and Rivers, which is no more than Aping the Country by a forc'd Hypochriſy; which makes no ſmall Addition to the excellency of our Rural Enjoyments, and ſerves no more than a <hi>Foyl,</hi> to make a greater Illuſtration of her <hi>Beauty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We might further inſiſt on the many other Pleaſures that attend a Country Life, as <hi>Hunting, Hawking,</hi> &amp;c. but theſe being wholly out of the way of our <hi>Exciſe-Man,</hi> (to whom only we confine our Diſcourſe) we ſhall wave it here, though cannot avoid the deſcription our Poet gives of that part of it, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly accompanies him.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:34357:56"/>
               <q>
                  <l>— The Country we behold</l>
                  <l>Deckt in her <hi>Parl'ment Robes,</hi> and richeſt Mold</l>
                  <l>A Native Mint ſhines in each Marygold.</l>
                  <l>Behold the Earth made Paradiſe! Below</l>
                  <l>A Conſtellation doth of Roſes grow;</l>
                  <l>Whole <hi>Clouds of Violets wave,</hi> whoſe annual Spice</l>
                  <l>Offers an Everlaſting Sacrifice:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mantles of Pinks</hi> (like Rainbows) do diſplay</l>
                  <l>Their Beams, and <hi>Lillies</hi> make a <hi>Milky-way.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>See how th adopted Boughs are thatch't, whoſe Main</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Phoebus</hi> Curling Irons are criſp'd again:</l>
                  <l>And by the Cutwork which from thence it made,</l>
                  <l>Checquers the Ground thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Twilight of a Shade.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:34357:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <p>AND as the <hi>Pleaſures</hi> that attend this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching Life, are far above the mean Deſcription of a Pen that is not capable of <hi>admiring</hi> enough, much leſs the <hi>deſcribing;</hi> ſo the <hi>Profit,</hi> that is the infallible <hi>Reſult,</hi> ought at leaſt to be ſomewhat regarded, and a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on.</p>
               <p>Here is a Theme that requires a much more acurate <hi>Pen</hi> than mine, which as it never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, ſo owns it ſelf wholly <hi>incapable,</hi> even ſo much as <hi>inſinuating</hi> thoſe Pleaſures and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that here daily court and follow him, but upon the ſame account <hi>one</hi> ſpeaks of, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his attempt of deſcribing that, which would not (like our preſent Subject) admit of it.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Staffs</hi> cannot go, and yet enable him</l>
                  <l>That wants Aſſiſtance to his feeble Limb;</l>
                  <l>Tho <hi>Whetſtones</hi> cannot cut at all, they may</l>
                  <l>Do ſervice, and make Knives as ſharp as they</l>
                  <l>Themſelves are blunt; And they who cannot <hi>Ring,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>Jangling</hi> may Toll better <hi>Ringers in.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>I ſhall therefore only briefly ſubdivide the Profit that attends him into two Particulars,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:34357:57"/>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, That of the <hi>Perſon,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Pecuniary Advantages:</hi> And ſecondly, That of the <hi>Mind,</hi> reſpecting the exerciſing it in the Art of <hi>Contemplation</hi> and <hi>Reflection,</hi> in <hi>both</hi> which you will find he exceeds the reſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> is the only Perſon that can poſſibly enjoy theſe <hi>Pleaſures</hi> without <hi>Expence;</hi> for what others purchaſe at a dear Rate, he receives with <hi>Interest;</hi> for whereas they are neceſſitated to <hi>pay</hi> for their Pleaſures, he is <hi>paid</hi> for them: And whereas the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Mankind, who have an extravagant fruition of them, are <hi>undone</hi> in their <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> you will certainly find him <hi>made;</hi> ſo that he <hi>thrives,</hi> when others <hi>decay;</hi> he is <hi>happy,</hi> when others are <hi>miſerable;</hi> and <hi>Rich,</hi> where others receive a <hi>Beggary:</hi> So that he only can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſaid to enjoy them without an <hi>Interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or grating <hi>Diſſatisfaction;</hi> or that which is much more intolerable, the being accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for them in a <hi>Goal</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, The extraordinary Advantages he receives by <hi>Contemplation</hi> and <hi>Reflection,</hi> are not to be forgotten; the Profits of which need not here be enlarg'd on, ſince a <hi>Reverend</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">R. D. Occaſional Reflections.</note> 
                  <hi>Author</hi> has exactly perform'd it: ſo
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34357:58"/>I ſhall only ſay here, that he improves every Object, for he well knows that as <hi>Natura nihil ficit fruſtra,</hi> in relation to their <hi>inward</hi> quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the good of Mankind, ſo he alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders, that the leaſt of them adminiſters an improvement of the <hi>outward;</hi> for the moſt minute Object affords naturally ſuch <hi>Reflections,</hi> as are alſo extraordinary advantageous to the improving the <hi>inward Faoulties</hi> of the <hi>Mind;</hi> He conſiders how <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> as well as <hi>mean</hi> it is, to contradict the very <hi>Intention</hi> of his <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which he undoubtedly does, that does not ſtill perſiſt in Knowledge, and daily advance thoſe Qualifications Providence has been ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable as to endow him with; for he that does not encreaſe them, and paſſes his Life without improving them. ought certainly to have the reſt of his Life taken from him. The World (ſays Dr. <hi>Browne</hi>) was made to be <hi>inhabited</hi> by <hi>Beaſts,</hi> but <hi>ſtudied</hi> and <hi>contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plated</hi> by <hi>Man:</hi> 'tis the Debt of our Reaſon we owe to <hi>GOD:</hi> and the Homage we ought to pay for not being <hi>Beaſts,</hi> without this, the World is ſtill as though it had not been, or as it was before the <hi>Sixth Day,</hi> whereas yet there was not a Creature that could conceive, or ſay there was a World. The Wiſdom of <hi>GOD</hi> receives ſmall Honour from thoſe <hi>Vulgar Heads</hi> that rudely ſtare about, and with a groſs <hi>Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticity</hi> admire his Works; thoſe highly magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy Him, whoſe judicious enquiry into his Acts, and deliberate reſearch into 'tis Creatures, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the Duty of a devout and learned Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34357:58"/>For the bare ſenſe of <hi>Sight,</hi> makes no diſtinction between <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> and the irrational <hi>Brute;</hi> there being no outward Object, but what is as viſible to <hi>thoſe</hi> (if not more) than to the <hi>Rational;</hi> and 'tis the improving the <hi>Facul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the Soul, that ought to give us the diſcriminating Character or <hi>Men,</hi> which is ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rly perform'd, and that (as any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Man will find upon trial) from the moſt ſlight and meaneſt occaſions, and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties imaginable.</p>
               <p>Among the innumerable Reflections on theſe outward Objects, which he da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly meets with, I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iefly in ſinuate a few, that you may gueſs at the reſt; not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that you may conclude his Thoughts never to be idle, or the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his Jedgme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> capable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodically to digeſt them; but that he does it too, and draws ſuch natural Inferences and Concluſions from this Art of <hi>Occaſional Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection,</hi> which he infallibly finds both <hi>profitable</hi> and <hi>pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſees not a <hi>Swallow,</hi> but it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts him in mind of <hi>ungrateſul Perſons,</hi> who (like that unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging Birth) are of no <hi>uſe</hi> to us, but leave us, when they have ſerv'd their own turn.</p>
               <p>He views not the <hi>Tulip,</hi> or <hi>Marygold,</hi> but he immediately has diſplay'd a <hi>Flatterer</hi> in his thoughts; for as 'tis the natural quality of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34357:59"/>thoſe Flowers to open and ſhut with the <hi>San,</hi> ſo it is with him, to follow its motions, and never attend it but when ſhining proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perouſly.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Mole</hi> he beholds not, without having a particular Eye to the <hi>Avaritious;</hi> neither can he look on the <hi>Circle</hi> in a <hi>Stream,</hi> that never ceaſeth to enlarge it ſelf, without a <hi>Reflection</hi> on the ſame effects of <hi>Ambition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He meets not the diſpatching Poſt on his way, but he preſently conſiders that his Life haſtens with an equal (if not greater) Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, and therefore commands an Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it: Neither doth he look on a <hi>Glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm,</hi> but he preſently ſhapes in his Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a true Idea of the moſt formal Hypotrite, whom he concludes to appear with the ſame deluding Splendor.</p>
               <p>Theſe are ſome few of the many Inferences he continually draws from thoſe outward Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that inevitably attend him, which we might enlarge on even to a Volume.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>But ſtay—His Worth exceeds our Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t's ſtore,</l>
                  <l>I can't commend 'till he deſerves no more</l>
                  <l>It far tranſcends all our Magnetick Praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Who writes him well may well deſerve the Bayes.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:34357:59"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <p>BUT leſt there ſhould be any thing that is really charming in it ſelf, or that which can be properly ſaid to be capable of yielding any Pleaſure below, which our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> does not enjoy in a very great degree; or leaſt the rough and tedious ways, and ſolitary courſe of living, ſhould be ſaid to extenuate the Pleaſures he meets with in a Rural Life; or that this ſatisfaction ſhould be ſomewhat pall'd by a continu'd enjoyment of them, and conſequently that there ſhould be any variety the <hi>Fates</hi> allow of, as agreeable to the active Inclinations of rational Mortals, that ſhould not infallibly attend their <hi>Favourite,</hi> we ſhall lead him from his <hi>Country,</hi> to his ambulatory Enjoyments of the <hi>City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> in his late Privacy cannot lie long <hi>conceald;</hi> for what by his obliging Behaviour, and extraordinary Qualifications, hourly demonſtrated in theſe his Country Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements, with a due obſervation of thoſe Obligations he lay under, by an exact per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. of the Truſt repos'd in him, he is taken notice of <hi>above,</hi> and admir'd <hi>below,</hi> which produces an immediate Reſolution of his being no longer <hi>hid</hi> in <hi>Woods</hi> and <hi>Fields,</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:34357:60"/>but to be a more publick <hi>Pattern</hi> (I muſt not ſay leſs, and cannot more) for the reſt of Mankind.</p>
               <p>And here I might particularize the ſeveral Pleaſures and Advantages that inevitably at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him in it, as improving the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> by the Company of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earned Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And though as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> juſt now inſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e'd, the Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Contemptation:</hi> and <hi>Reading</hi> (which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low} a Country Life) are extraordinary, yet this is the certain place for exerciſing it; the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt</hi> being but the <hi>Theorick,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> the <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctick</hi> Part: for <hi>Converſation</hi> (which is chiefly found in a City Life) exhibits <hi>growth</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> to that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> which was but dung'd} in the Country. It might be further affirm'd, That here only is ſound that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Language,</hi> which qualifies a Perſon for the greateſt of Employments and Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, and that (as ſome are ſo unkind to ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy) they live in the Country not only <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known,</hi> but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknowing</hi> too: Action (as I ſaid before) being the chiefeſt part of Knowledge, and that is no where to be demonſtrated more that in the City; which he will alſo find to be the chiefeſt, if not the only place where a Porſon can infullildy meet <hi>Preferment</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for the obſcurity of a Rural Life, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces a very great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſumption of a <hi>Neaples <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra,</hi> if happily he can keep himſelf there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And 'tis moſt certain that there are many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Qualifications lie <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſting</hi> and <hi>dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:34357:60"/>in the Country, which might find (as well as give) great Advantages to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they live under, if they embrac'd a more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ublick Character by a city Life.</p>
               <p>But my natural Humour and Inclination command me net to proceed, which admires only a Retirement, and abominates all things that look like Confuſion; and leaſt the Reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhould wheedle me into another extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Extaſy and Admiration, I ſhall for bear enlarging any more in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, and give it leave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſinuate, That although thoſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Pleaſures may merit and intrance our Affection, yet<note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Travels. p. 188.</note> when one ariſes from a great Meal, no Delicacies, now much ſoever they may tempt him at another time, can provoke his appetite; ſo freely confeſs, that the late ſight and remembrance of Rural Enjoyments, have ſo whetted my Defites, that I cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the admiring or deſcribing any other, without Regret and Surfeit. And indeed they have been ſo extravagantly intrancing, that though the Diverſions the City affords, might at ſome other time be tolerably captivating in my opinion, yet upon this <hi>Hint,</hi> I cannot allow them the leaſt room or entertainment; which Suggeſtion obliges me to an <hi>Apology,</hi> and to atone for the Injury done my <hi>Inclinations,</hi> but eſpecially to the <hi>Country,</hi> by contradicting the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34357:61"/>
                  <hi>first,</hi> and by offering ſo much to the prejudice of the <hi>last;</hi> for the intolerable Preſumption that there ſhould be any Life that could be admitted <hi>in Competition with it:</hi> And ſuppoſing no greater <hi>Satisfaction</hi> can be given her, (the former having been <hi>mentally</hi> perform'd) I ſhall conclude with her Excellency in the words of the Poet:
<q>
                     <l>Nature does only here in Triumph vide,</l>
                     <l>And makes this place the ground of all her Pride,</l>
                     <l>Where every Tree a fruitful Iſſue hears</l>
                     <l>Of each Variety that Mortals chears:</l>
                     <l>And all the Shrubs with ſparkling Spangles ſhew</l>
                     <l>Like Morning Sunſhine tinſilling the Dew;</l>
                     <l>Here in green Meadows ſits Eternal <hi>May,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Purſling the Margents with perpetual Day;</l>
                     <l>And that ſo double-guil'd, as that no Night</l>
                     <l>Can ever Ruſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>enamel of the Light;</l>
                     <l>The ſportive Shepherds of rich Flocks rehearſe,</l>
                     <l>And to their pleaſant Pipes chant Rural Verſe,</l>
                     <l>Seeking his angry <hi>Godhead</hi> to appeaſe,</l>
                     <l>Whom only wealthy Flocks and Herds can pleaſe:</l>
                     <l>Here checquer'd Flow'rs in the Meadows ſpring,</l>
                     <l>And here the Birds their untaught Notes do ſing</l>
                     <l>With Glory here, <hi>Flora</hi> the Earth arrays</l>
                     <l>With Violets ſhe embroiders all the Ways.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:34357:61"/>
               <head>CHAP. XX.</head>
               <p>I Deſcend to the next Particular intended to be mentioned in relation to the <hi>Excellency</hi> of our <hi>Exciſe-Man's Office,</hi> which is, that it even neceſſitates him, or (if you'l have it ſo) commands him to be <hi>diligent,</hi> and conſequently he is abſolutely deliver'd from (that <hi>Devil's Cuſhion,</hi> and Banc of <hi>Mankind</hi>) <hi>Idleneſs, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will or no;</hi> for though <hi>Neceſſity makes the Old Wife Trot,</hi> it will make him <hi>Gallop</hi> for the exact performance of that Duty he is ſo well rewarded for, by lying under a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of being good; for while our imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are exercis'd by a continual Var<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, of differing Objects, they are entertain'd with that which is at leaſt very near it, if not excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: ſo that this baniſhment of <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers them from all the <hi>beginnings,</hi> as well as <hi>ſteps</hi> and <hi>degrees,</hi> of that which may be term'd <hi>bad;</hi> for it is generally obſerv'd, that there is often but very little ſpace of time between doing of <hi>nothing,</hi> and doing of <hi>ill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I ſhall not imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtinently enlarge, by the robbing of <hi>Poet;</hi> of <hi>Sentences,</hi> for the expoſing of this Vice, as that of <hi>Pho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ylides:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:34357:62"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Of all Mankind 'tis the Belief,</l>
                        <l>That every I dle Man's a Thief.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Or that of <hi>Heſiod:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>—'Twas ever ſed,</l>
                        <l>The Idle Man deſerves no Bread.}</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>With many others that might be eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand'd; but ſhall only here obſerve, that it was held ſo notoriouſly ſcandalous by the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients,</hi> that we find in <hi>Juſtin</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Lib</hi> 32.</note> , that the <hi>Daci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as an eternal Stamp of <hi>Infamy,</hi> were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated by a Law of <hi>Oler</hi> their <hi>King,</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate their Sloth, by laying their Feet where they ſhould reſt their Heads; and to perform thoſe Offices and Services to their Wives, which their Wives were accuſtom'd to do to them. He knows that <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his <hi>Adages,</hi> calls a <hi>Slothful Man, Mulieris Podex:</hi> What a ſhame then is it to be worſe than <hi>Animal Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationale! Nihil est ſordidius</hi> (ſaith <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi>) <hi>nihil cruddius quam ſi Rempublicam ii arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt, qui nshil in eam ſuo labore conſerunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Charity</hi> has been ever eſteem'd the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34357:62"/>
                  <hi>Principal</hi> of Vertues, both by <hi>Ethnicks</hi> and <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologiſts;</hi> and though the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ô the extremity of her Blindneſs, pretend; to engroſs that Heaven-engaging Vertue to her ſelf, yet if her Inducements, by Merit, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> and <hi>Hers,</hi> will not any way admit of a Competition, ſince we find his Principles are founded on the true No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Ends of Charity, by his ſpontancous Contributions: So that although he has not, with Her, erected <hi>Colledges,</hi> and other <hi>Pompous Structures,</hi> whoſe Grandure outvies the moſt eminent Pieces of Architecture in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; yet his <hi>Aſylum</hi> for the Afflicted, his <hi>Competency</hi> for the Diſtreſſed, and his <hi>Relief</hi> for the Aged, who any way deſerv'd it in their Vigor, are to all conſpicuous, and will reinain as Trophies to their Honour:
<q>
                     <l>Whilst the Celeſtial Orbs in Order roul,</l>
                     <l>And turn their Flames about the ſtedfast <hi>Pole.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But laſtly, If we conſider Man in his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex,</hi> in his beſt and worſt Senſe, and take him in his Youth or Age, he will not merit Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; for it matters not whether the Eyes of Reaſon were never <hi>open'd,</hi> or whether they have been and are <hi>cloſed,</hi> ſince they cannot <hi>ſee;</hi> and it's evident that is of no validity, if the <hi>Chin</hi> be <hi>white,</hi> whether it be with, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Hair;</hi> ſince the Madneſs and Folly of 16, and the Dotage and Diſtempers of 60 are equivalent. Man we own to be that rational
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34357:63"/>Commander of all Terreſtrials, that Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Monarch, who almoſt annihilates thoſe Individuals with a Glance, who therefore cringe, and moſt ſpontaneouſly obey; Man is not denid to be that Spark of Heaven, that mortal Angel, that commands a Dread upon appearance, yet muſt it be allow'd that this only is a Dept to him that boldly juſtifies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be ſo, and therefore, though he is a <hi>glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ious Qrb,</hi> yet lies he under an <hi>Eclipſe</hi> in <hi>Youth</hi> and <hi>Age,</hi> in which he ever muſt <hi>conceal</hi> his <hi>Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If then <hi>Mankind</hi> contains the <hi>Excellencies of the whole <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe in Epitome,</hi> it muſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently exhibit an <hi>amazing Excellency</hi> to the <hi>Exciſe,</hi> that receives only the moſt <hi>excellent part of Him,</hi> by rejecting the Impertinencies of Nonage, as uſeleſs Animals fit only for the <hi>Cradle,</hi> by admitting none but the <hi>robust and ſenſible,</hi> and by excluding that <hi>weak and decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid Clas,</hi> who only claim the priviledge of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing troubleſom.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>But had I <hi>Virgil</hi>'s Verſe, or <hi>Tully</hi>'s Tongue,</l>
                  <l>Or raping Numbers like the <hi>Thracian</hi>'s Song,</l>
                  <l>I have a Theme would make the Rocks to dance,</l>
                  <l>And ſurly Beaſts that thrô the Deſarts prance,</l>
                  <l>Hie from their Caves, and every gloomy Den,</l>
                  <l>To wonder at the <hi>Excellence</hi> of Men.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:34357:63"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXI.</head>
               <p>THus have you had a brief and lame Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Excellencies of our Exciſe-Man</hi> in the <hi>knowledge of the Arts, Men and Laws;</hi> together with the many <hi>Advantages,</hi> as well as <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> that naturally reſult from that Employment, and conſequently are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable Attendants on <hi>Him;</hi> I muſt now crave leave to ſubjoin ſome ſew <hi>Queries,</hi> and ſhall make no other Apology, then</p>
               <p>—<hi>Non ſeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſemper.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. Whether he ought not to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd <hi>a great Scholar,</hi> ſince he is continually <hi>poring on his Book?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. Whether there is not ſome <hi>Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> between <hi>him</hi> and <hi>Diogenes,</hi> ſince they equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>affect the Tub?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 3. Whether he underſtands not <hi>Art Notoria,</hi> ſince he brings all things to a <hi>Circle?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 4. Whether he is not a great Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the <hi>Old Philoſophy,</hi> ſince he utterly abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates a <hi>Vacuum?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 5. Whether he muſt not be a very <hi>grave Perſon,</hi> that affects <hi>Solidity?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 6. Whether he muſt not be a <hi>proſound Man,</hi> that takes the <hi>depth</hi> of every thing?</item>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:34357:64"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 7. Whether he muſt not be <hi>extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy,</hi> that ſo well knows that which is call'd <hi>Content?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 8. Whether <hi>our Exciſe-Man</hi> is not an <hi>extraordinary honest Man,</hi> ſince he does all things upon the <hi>Square?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 9. Whether he can be ſaid to be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant,</hi> that ever walks within <hi>Compaſs?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 10. Whether he ought not to be thought an <hi>excellent Aſtronomer,</hi> ſince he ſo often conſults the <hi>Stars?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 11. Whether he can <hi>Err,</hi> that ever walks by <hi>Rule?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 12. Whether he ought not to be reckon'd well-skill'd in <hi>Geography,</hi> that inſtead <hi>of Miles,</hi> can tell you the <hi>very Steps?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 13. Whether if <hi>in Luto there's Pluto,</hi> he ought not to be ſuppos'd very <hi>Rich,</hi> ſince he is continually ſearching the <hi>bottom of it?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 14. Whether he is not excellently <hi>skill'd in Muſick,</hi> ſince he ſo well <hi>underſtands the Baſe?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 15. Whether he can <hi>do any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs,</hi> ſince he does all things by <hi>Warrant?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 16. Whether he <hi>affects not the Clergy,</hi> ſince he infallibly allows a <hi>Tenth?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 17. Whether he is not a good <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,</hi> ſince he muſt be an allow'd <hi>Peripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetick?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 18. Whether he can be <hi>baniſh'd,</hi> that is never at <hi>home?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 19. Whether he can <hi>want,</hi> that has <hi>Victuall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs</hi> enough?</item>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:34357:64"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 20. Whether he can be thought <hi>Idle,</hi> that is always in <hi>Motion?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 21. Whether he can be an <hi>ordinary Man,</hi> that is a Man of <hi>Figure?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 22. Whether he ought not to be <hi>highly eſteem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d,</hi> ſince he is a Man of great <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 23. Whether he is not a <hi>qualified Poet,</hi> that is ſo excellently <hi>vers'd in Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 24. Whether if a <hi>Mean</hi> be the moſt <hi>deſirable in all our Actions,</hi> he is not <hi>extremely qualified,</hi> that is converſant therein continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally?</item>
               </list>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus in</hi> jocoſe <hi>and</hi> ſerious Terms <hi>we find</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th'</hi> Exciſe-Man <hi>far</hi> tranſcends <hi>all</hi> human kind;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For he that every</hi> charming Science <hi>knows,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Can never the</hi> triumphant Garland <hi>loſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII.</head>
               <p>I Have now finiſh'd my intended <hi>Eſſay</hi> on the <hi>Excellency</hi> of our <hi>Exciſe-Man,</hi> and altho it be far ſhort of what might have been done in <hi>more time,</hi> and by a <hi>better Pen,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently an <hi>Apology</hi> might be here expected both by <hi>himſelf,</hi> as well as the <hi>Reader,</hi> (the <hi>former</hi> for performing it no better, and the <hi>latter</hi> for attempting it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all;) yet I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell the <hi>first,</hi> that altho my time would not
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34357:65"/>ſuffer me to diſcover <hi>more,</hi> nor my <hi>Ability all,</hi> yet I have deliver'd <hi>ſome</hi> of his <hi>Perfections;</hi> which if true, then I muſt inform the <hi>last,</hi> that it was a Law among the <hi>Parthians,</hi> that whenever a Notorious Malefactor was brought on the Stage, a ſevere Scrutiny was made into the Actions of his whole Life; and if, upon the total, the number of his good Deeds exceeded thoſe of his ill, he was <hi>ipſo facto</hi> quitted: If therefore this <hi>demands a Pardon,</hi> I ſhall not endeavour an additional <hi>Tryal of the Reader's Patience,</hi> but only ſubjoin ſome few Lines, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> Demeanor under the <hi>greatest of his Afflictions,</hi> I mean when his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappineſs</hi> has <hi>arriv'd</hi> to that <hi>Extremity,</hi> as the receiving his <hi>Diſcharge,</hi> and that under a double Notion, <hi>viz.</hi> when he is.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Guilty.</hi> 2. <hi>Innocent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In relation to the <hi>first</hi> I ſhall only ſay, that he is extremely ſerſible of his Miſcarriages, and his innate M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deſty is ſo extravagantly prevalent, that he immediately chalks out a new (tho honeſt) way of ſubſiſting, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Brow</hi> to make his appearance for, and conſequently dares not attempt, a re-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But <hi>ſecondly,</hi> Our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> (as is prere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited) boaſts of an <hi>Accompliſhment,</hi> which he ever highly eſteems, and is this, That no Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune can be a Sorprize: He knows that <hi>Tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Goddeſs</hi> (who glories chieſly in her Fickleneſs) delights in nothing but Viciſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes; he has read the Poets, who aſſure him,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:34357:65"/>that She is the Rectreſs of all our Actions, and Arbitreſs of all ſublunary Affairs, and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a continual preparation for Her <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> for ſince <hi>Diadems</hi> themſelves find no du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but are frequently attended with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Mutations, he cannot expect an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption; for our <hi>Life</hi> is compared to a Game at Dice, where we ought to throw for what is moſt commodious for us, but to be content with our Caſts, let them be never ſo unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; we cannot make what Chances we pleaſe turn up, if we play fair, this lies out of out power: that which is within it, is to accept pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently what Providence ſhall alot us, and ſo to adjuſt things in their proper places, that what is our own, may be di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſed of to the beſt advantage; and what hath happen'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Will, may never give occaſion of offence to us: Nay, he is ſatisfied it frequently proves moſt advantagious to him; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho Innocence may be <hi>attacqu'd,</hi> yet can it never be <hi>vanquiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi> He knows the <hi>Cypres</hi> the more weight is impos'd on it, the more it grows, and flouriſhes by being depreſs'd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the fragrant <hi>Camomile</hi> retitlers a great increaſe of her bewitching Odors, by being trod and trampled on. Examples amongſt the <hi>Ancients</hi> he finds to be numerous: Thus the baniſhmort of <hi>Diogenes</hi> was the occaſion of his being a Philoſopher; and when <hi>Zeno</hi> heard that the only Ship he had left, was ſunk by an unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Tempeſt, with all the rich Cargo that was in her, he brake out into this Exclamation,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:34357:66"/>
                  <hi>Fortune! I applaud thy Comrivance, who by this means haſt reduced me to a Threadbare Cloak, and to walk in the</hi> Piazza <hi>of the</hi> Stoicks. He knows our Bodies are compounded of thoſe Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als which command a daily Revolution, and we ſhould never know the real and intrinſick value of that firſt and choiceſt of Bleſſings, Light, did it not ſometimes meet with a Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and continually attended with a ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Darkneſs. If theſe Alterations then are daily repreſented to us, they are therefore become familiar, and conſequently cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a Surprize but to the Vulgar, who are not qualified with any Perception but what is inſtantly ocular: How then can it be rational to admire, if that melts, whoſe Nature is Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quefaction? if that burns, which is combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible? if watry Humidities conglaciate? if the determination of Quickſilver is Fixation? that of Milk, Coagulation? and that of Oil, or all unctuous Bodies, Incraſſation? And ſo by a parity of Reaſon, if that periſheth, whoſe Law of Conſtitution was to be made, that it might be attended with Contingencies; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therefore can ſeize him that can contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict his expectations, nay, they are never fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated but when they meet him not. <hi>Theſeus</hi> in <hi>Euripides</hi> ſeems to be excellently well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for Events:
<q>
                     <l>This wholſom Precept from the Wiſe I learn,</l>
                     <l>To think of Miſery without Concern:</l>
                     <l>My meditating Thoughts are always ſpent</l>
                     <l>Either on Death, or elſe on Baniſhment.</l>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:34357:66"/>
                     <l>Foreſight of Evils doth employ my Mind,</l>
                     <l>That me without Defence they may not find;</l>
                     <l>And tho in Ambuſcade the miſchief lies,</l>
                     <l>Kill me it may, but ſhall me not ſurprize.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To proſecute this a little farther: It's plain, Induſtrious Nature inſtructs us, and inculcates this fix'd and ſteady preparation, and that from the moſt minute Objects imaginable; the very Trees, Plants and Vegetables evidently demonſtrate this wheeling Inſtability; ſince its viſible that not any of their Leafs remain, but in <hi>Autumn</hi> loſe their Verdure, and are ſwept away by every Blaſt of <hi>Boreas:</hi> Thus their Sap retires, which immediately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands a deadneſs, and dejected nakedneſs in the moſt glorious of their <hi>Limbs;</hi> which by the Approach and ſweet Careſſes of the <hi>Spring,</hi> are attended with all their priſtine life and ſplendor: And we yearly ſee the embroyder'd <hi>Summer,</hi> that exhibits thoſe bewitching Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which appear ſo grateful to <hi>Humane Race,</hi> to be continually ſucceeded by the <hi>Snowy Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruque,</hi> and the moſt <hi>diſmal Concomitants</hi> of a <hi>melancholy</hi> and <hi>barren Winter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Accidents then being inevitable and univerſal, our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> Reſolutions are irrevocably ſedate and ready; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to him they never can prove unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected or novel: He is extremely ſenſible of the mutability of all Terreſtrials, and joins with <hi>Euripides,</hi> when he tells us,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:34357:67"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>From ſmall Beginnings our Misfortunes grow,</l>
                     <l>And little Rubs our Feet do overthrow;</l>
                     <l>A Smile is quickly chang'd into a Frown,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Low</hi> things go up, and <hi>lofty</hi> things go <hi>down.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The natural Conſequent of the Premiſes our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi> knows to be, that they ſhall not therefore in the leaſt deject him, ſince conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thoughts can never attack him, nor poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes he a tainted Breaſt: Innocence is the nobleſt Remedy, and the greateſt comfort in, and infallible Cure of our innumerable Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; and though his <hi>Fortunes</hi> may (nay muſt) be <hi>chequer'd,</hi> yet his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> are all <hi>white</hi> and <hi>innocent,</hi> which therefore cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate a boldneſs not any way to be extenuated. He fronts the Perfecution with an undaunted and unalterable Brow, and ſmiles at the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Cenſures of the Malevolent; this is it that buoys him up in the moſt impetuous Tempeſt, and makes the Caſtle of his Breaſt to be ever inexpugnable: He knows theſe Changes to be naturally incident, and therefore as he is in a continual expectation of them, ſo does he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably receive them, and remembers that none but the <hi>unthinking Crew</hi> can be hereby eaſt down, and none but <hi>Fools</hi> repine. Thus <hi>Pindar:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>The Gods unequal have us Mortals vex'd,</l>
                     <l>For to <hi>one Good, two Evils</hi> are annex'd:</l>
                     <l>They pay a <hi>ſingle Joy,</hi> with <hi>double Care,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Fools</hi> ſuch Diſpenſations cannot bear.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:34357:67"/>
               <p>If then theſe Revolutions muſt of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> attend him, he concludes too they muſt of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> be born with: He knows it then to be a moſt exceſſive weakneſs, to lie impatiently concern'd under a Load that is not (nor was not) any way to be avoided; and therefore ſubmiſſively receives them without an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and conſequently adheres to <hi>Plutarch:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>If Fortune prove extravagantly kind,</l>
                     <l>Above its Temper do not raiſe thy Mind;</l>
                     <l>If She diſclaims thee like a jilting Dame,</l>
                     <l>Be not dejected but be ſtill the Jame;</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Gold unchang'd</hi> amidſt the <hi>hotteſt</hi> ſlame</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Exciſe-Man</hi>'s being thus prepar'd for all imaginable Events, produces alſo this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quential Inference, That he is not poor or miſerable. He foreſaw the Happineſs was not to be durable, and did therefore prepare for its departure. He embrac'd the Critical Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute ſo, as to ſurvive when it vaniſhed. He concludes that that Perſon muſt be very ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, that while Fortune ſmiles lays not up a <hi>Reſerve</hi> (ſince it is as much virtue to hear a good Fortune as an ill) for its <hi>Reverſe;</hi> and to be <hi>now</hi> in <hi>want,</hi> is a demonſtrative Argument of his <hi>want</hi> of <hi>Senſe before;</hi> ſo that to be out at <hi>Heels at last,</hi> was to be out of his <hi>Wits at first;</hi> ſince he is thereby become miſerable, and conſequently the ſubject only of diſdain and ſcorn: For it's daily viſible, that <hi>Poverty</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:34357:68"/>creates a ſeparation of the greateſt Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the total deſtruction of the moſt cemented Intimates; for he that a month be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wanted to <hi>know your Commands,</hi> utterly ſhuns you now, as if that Corps muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Plague, that is accompanied with Rags; and you may as well go naked, as to have Breeches, and nothing in them: 'tis in this only the Friendſhip of the Age conſiſts. And this he is aſſur'd of, that if once he is thus reduc'd, not one (nay not one of thoſe on whom he has heap'd the utmoſt of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours) will be ſeen with him, or ſpeak in his <hi>Vind cati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n:</hi> ſo it ſeems, that he that is <hi>poor,</hi> muſt be <hi>conſequently bad,</hi> and <hi>guilty</hi> of all the <hi>intolerable Enormities imaginable.</hi> If you are once <hi>bruis'd,</hi> you muſt <hi>heal</hi> your ſelf; and your <hi>Groans</hi> will be <hi>drown'd</hi> with their <hi>tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Acclamations.</hi> If you are <hi>ſhipwreck'd</hi> by a ſtorm of <hi>Tears,</hi> you may have your <hi>own Sighs</hi> to blow you right again. If you are once <hi>level'd</hi> with the ground, you muſt <hi>raiſe your ſelf,</hi> or <hi>lie there,</hi> and be <hi>trampled on;</hi> ſo that if once the <hi>Deſtinies</hi> do <hi>triumph</hi> over us, not any Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>fails.</hi> If once our <hi>Stage</hi> of Life proves <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical,</hi> we ſhall never change the <hi>Scene</hi> by the aſſiſtance of any adjacent Actor, or Spectator, but be miſcrable to the lateſt <hi>Epilogue;</hi> and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereby become the fitteſt Object for that poor comfort of Calamity, <hi>Pity.</hi> But I have ſufficiently dilated on this Topick in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Diſcourſe, and already largely ſhew'd
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:34357:68"/>you our <hi>Exciſe-Man's</hi> Sentiments herein, ſo I ſhall here wave its further proſecution.</p>
               <p>The concluſive Deduction is, That our <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe-Man</hi> is not abuſive to thoſe who even oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd his moſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njust Diſcharge;</hi> nor has he hard thoughts of thoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon perform'd it: Reſpecting the <hi>former,</hi> he knows, that though they have done him an Injury far beyond any Reparation, a Prejudice above the reach of Satisfaction, and a Wrong which could not be ſupported with Patience by any but himſelf, and no one's Charity but his could pardon; yet his unſpotted and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain'd Innocence fortifies, and is the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal <hi>Arſenal</hi> which infallibly provides him with the moſt powerful <hi>Arms</hi> to hinder his being <hi>vanquiſh'd.</hi> He ſmiles at the petty Intrigues of theſe Diminutives, who therefore dread his <hi>Preſence,</hi> which creates a Sweat beyond a <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi> and whoſe Knees are mutual <hi>Anvils,</hi> that <hi>beat</hi> a Deſperation, whilſt be triumphantly ſits <hi>unſullied</hi> like the <hi>Lilly,</hi> and thus enthroned, reigas in <hi>untainted Innocence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In relation to the <hi>latter,</hi> he concludes, That as no compacted Duſt can be infallible, ſo the moſt towring parts and knowing Mortal, have not eſcap'd an Impoſition from the ſubtle, tho abominable Artifices of thoſe who no way merit the Character of Men; and ſince their Intentions are always guided by the ſtricleſt
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:34357:69"/>Rules of Probity and Juſtice, he therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not cenſure the reſult, though it is not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately attended with the real Conſequent of it. Beſides, he ſees them frequently detected, and conſequently a ſmall ſpace of time will produce its deſired Effects, and himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore re-eſtabliſhed. In the mean time his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour is ever modeſtly ſubmiſſive, and with a ſedate Contentment waits a ſuitable Reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation of his moſt inoffenſive Behaviour, and ſurvives, in hope of its being crown'd with an agreeable ſucceſs. And indeed it is the only happineſs of him that is depriv'd of all other; for Hope is the greateſt Antidote againſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, and the infallible Cordial againſt all impending Miſeries; and although it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly deceitful, yet it is of this good uſe to us, that while we are travelling through this life, it conducts us an caſier and more pleaſant way to our Journies END.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:34357:69"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
